<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The worlds wonder, or the Quakers blazing starr: with an astronomical judgment given upon the same, from 2 Cor. 11.13, 14, 15. Proving them to be altogether deluded by Satan, both in their judgments and walkings: together with a probable conjecture of the end of the world, and the estate of things in the interval. / By Edmund Skipp preacher of the Gospel unto the people at Bodenham in Herefordshire.</title>
            <author>Skipp, Edmund.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3949</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E829_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207389</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866443</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866443</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118718</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93315)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118718)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 126:E829[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The worlds wonder, or the Quakers blazing starr: with an astronomical judgment given upon the same, from 2 Cor. 11.13, 14, 15. Proving them to be altogether deluded by Satan, both in their judgments and walkings: together with a probable conjecture of the end of the world, and the estate of things in the interval. / By Edmund Skipp preacher of the Gospel unto the people at Bodenham in Herefordshire.</title>
                  <author>Skipp, Edmund.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 65, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills, and are to be sold at the sign of Sir John Oldcastle near Py-corner.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Febr. 28. 1654"; 5 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 2nd --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>End of the world --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118718:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Worlds Wonder, OR THE QUAKERS BLAZING STARR: WITH An Aſtronomical Judgment given upon the ſame, from 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13, 14, 15.</p>
            <p>Proving them to be altogether deluded by Satan, both in their judgments and walkings:</p>
            <p>Together with a probable conjecture of the end of the World, and the eſtate of things in the interval.</p>
            <p>By EDMUND SKIPP Preacher of the Goſpel unto the People at <hi>Bodenham</hi> in <hi>Herefordſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 24.24.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>There ſhall ariſe falſe <hi>Chriſts</hi> and falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſigns and wonders, in ſo much that (if it were poſſible) they ſhall deceive the very elect.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Sign of Sir <hi>John Oldcastle</hi> near <hi>Py-corner.</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118718:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118718:2"/>
            <head>To all thoſe who are willing to hold faſt the Faith of the Goſpel, and to be guided by the Truth, <hi>Grace, Mercy and Peace, from God the Father and the Lord</hi> JESUS CHRIST.</head>
            <p>TWo things have much moved my affections unto this Work follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</p>
            <p n="1">1. The one, that herein I might ſhew an humble acknowledgment of love unto the Lord who delivered my ſoul from under thoſe obſcurities which would utterly have diſabled me from being good to my own heart or others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That I might herein become a means of ſtaying and directing many an uneſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſoul to beware of thoſe horrible Deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and myſterious Deceits, which I have in this enſuing Treatiſe, with as much plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb facs="tcp:118718:3"/>and brevity as I judged convenient, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, for the ſake of all who are unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with theſe Apoſtacies, and are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſearch out untill they gain an eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment in the knowledg of the truth, as it is in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> For it would have been great unworthineſs in me, if when I was brought ſo experimentally to the knowledg of theſe unheard-of ways of Satans decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the hearts of poor Creatures under fair pretences and glorious ſhews of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and doing great ſigns and wonders, I ſhould have concealed from my generations ſuch things that were never yet manifeſted in ſuch a manner: The writing of common experiences either of good or evil operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, would neither have been an incitement to my Pen, or my Readers attention; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an extraordinary underſtanding in an extraordinary apparition of a prodigious Comet, whoſe beautifull ſcintillations make all the World to wonder what might be her fate, I durſt not for fear of wronging my own conſcience, but put my Light like a Candle upon the houſe-top, that ſo it might be ſeen into all the Regions of Goſpel-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions,
<pb facs="tcp:118718:3"/>manifeſting unto them, that this Monſter amongſt men, or this unnatural and unparalleld Planet promiſeth nothing but <hi>Vae miſero mihi,</hi> ſadneſs and loſs of all the riches of Gods grace, unto every ſoul that liveth under its malevolent and contagious influences. My Book will expound my Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legory, therefore I leave my Readers to that, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Their Servant in the Goſpel-ſervice, <hi>Edmund Skipp.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118718:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>COurteous Reader, I have here preſented thee with a little Tract, as my New-years Gift unto thee, and must deſire thee to carry a favorable aſpect in thy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment towards it and me, although thou maist finde it unpoliſhed, and void of ſuch a method and eloquence of words as thou mightst judg would better have become me and it, as well as many an acute <hi>Genius</hi> that ſhall honor it in the reading: But give me leave to tell thee truth, I have had but a fortnights time to begin and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh theſe lines, (which time I have through much diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty borrowed from my other Studies and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and they are now calling upon me for a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with double diligence) which hath been ſo little, that I have not had time to write any one line from the firſt to the laſt, twice, but am neceſſitated to ſend forth theſe Conceptions of mine thus Embrio-like into the open view of the world; and therefore I deſire to receive from thee what I ſhall be willing to give unto thee or any other in the like eaſe, a candid cenſure, deſiring alſo for thy good, that thou maiſt have an heart more ready to receive ſound judgment from it, than to give a wrong judgment upon it, I rest,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ever willing to ſerve thee in the Lord <hi>Edmund Skipp.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study at</hi> Bodenham <date>this New-years day ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the year 1654.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118718:4"/>
            <head>The Worlds Wonder, OR <hi>The</hi> QUAKERS <hi>Blazing Starr.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">A ſenſible Diſcovery of ſome high and ſpiritual Deluſions wrought by <hi>Antichrist</hi> in the hearts of of many poor Creatures, and eſpecially thoſe that go under the notion of QUAKERS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y that power which bringeth good out of evil, it cometh to paſs, that afflictions, fallings back, temptations, overwhelmings of the ſoul with a deluge of ſpiritual troubles, dejections and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolations, are many times profitable and <hi>teaching</hi> to the hearts of the Lords ſincere ones who are kept by himſelf through faith unto ſalvation, and they are laid in as ſo many ſeveral advantages, and as it were Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks to direct the ſoul in the perfect paths of peace, that they turn not aſide either to the right hand or to the left, ſo that it may make the children of the Moſt High admire his continued faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in his love and watchfulneſs manifeſted in their behalf, while they are run a whoring after their own inventions &amp; Satans deceivable transformings of himſelf into glorious appearances, words and actings. If a reaſonable heart ſhould but digeſt it ſelf into a methodical obſervation of the Lords Law of Retaliation, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26.14. <hi>to</hi> 34. and correſpondent dealings unto the ſtandings
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118718:5"/>and fallings of his creatures, it might be overcome in the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of that great patience, long-ſuffering and gentleneſs of the Lord to Apoſtates and unſtable-minded people, who have itching ears, carried about with every winde of Doctrine: But to the end he may gain himſelf a name in <hi>Judah,</hi> is he pleaſed to wait upon poor ſinners to be gracious unto them, and to ſuffer many of them to fall, to be tempted, to be darkned with cloudy and obſcure apprehenſions of the eternal being, that ſo their weakneſs and his ſtrength, their nothingneſs and his all-ſufficiency, their ſluggiſhneſs and his watchfulneſs might more clearly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in their proper place, and to make good his former word and practice in gathering his ſervants together out of all Lands whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had been ſcattered in the dark and cloudy day. And ſurely, were it not for the <hi>hopes</hi> of ſome ſuch glorious and wiſe end that the Lord doth now intend in the fulneſs of time to make known amongſt the ſons of men, it would miniſter cauſe of moſt unſpeakable ſorrow unto ſuch who are eſtabliſhed in the faith of our Lord JESUS CHRIST, to ſee ſo many forſaking their faith, and former knowledg and profeſſion of the truth, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead hereof believing lyes, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.11. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heed unto Doctrines of Devils, walking according to the ſuggeſtions of the Prince of Darkneſs, and every fooliſh, idle, fantaſtical imagination of their own deceitfull hearts.</p>
            <p>Theſe things do apparently teach the world to ſee, how vigilant that great Enemy of mankinde is, going about compaſſing the earth to and fro like a roaring Lion, ever ſeeking whom he may devour, and finding many poor ſouls eaſily enticed by him, and made his captives at his will, he enſnares them with his deceits, and engageth them ever more and more ſurely for himſelf, untill he maketh them his ſervants in willing obedience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.16. When a judicious man ſhall take a proſpect of the ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of all men living under the Goſpel-profeſſion, what a ſad thing it will be to conſider how much Satan hath beguiled the hearts of poor creatures through his lying vanities and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pretences of one ſort or other: while he can beguile men with putting pleaſant colours upon that ugly Monſter, ſin and unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, he will, but where he findeth himſelf too ſhort in this, then will he ſeek another way, and transform himſelf into an
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118718:5"/>Angel of light; that ſo under pretence of righteouſneſs he may beguile thoſe that would not yield unto unrighteouſneſs. This did <hi>Paul</hi> underſtand by the teachings of the Holy Ghoſt in his ſoul, when he ſpake ſo unto the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13, 14, 15. <hi>For ſuch are falſe Apostles, deceitfull workers, transforming themſelves into the Apostles of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the Apoſtle ſpeaketh forth the myſtery of that great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit which Satan is now working, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an Angel of light, and ſheweth us that like Teacher like Principle, like Maſter like Servant; for if he be transformed himſelf, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, It is no great thing if his Miniſters be transformed into Miniſters of Righteouſneſs. The word which the Apoſtle doth uſe for transformation if it be etymologically noted is ſomething <hi>teaching,</hi> for it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which cometh from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Habit us aut vestimentum corporis,</hi> the cloathing or apparelling of the body, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>trans,</hi> round about or over and over, which being put together, you ſhall finde, that Satans transformation of himſelf, is his <hi>feigning</hi> or diſſembling of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be what he is not; for whereas he is indeed and in truth one that acteth lying, unrighteouſneſs and iniquity, now being transformed or turned round about as it were, he acteth ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Truth, Righteouſneſs and Piety. And for as much as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle calleth him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an Angel of light, it is to help the people ſomething the better to underſtand the myſtery of his deceit; for generally he was (I ſuppoſe) by the people of that time, taken to be an Angel of darkneſs, as he is by the greateſt part of the people of our age; but indeed according to my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the nature of Angels,<note place="margin">The Angels as well as Man were capable of alteration in their creation.</note> he was created an Angel of Light, and not of Darkneſs, and ſo <hi>prima ab origine,</hi> or natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, he is an Angel of Light, but yet from the beginning (as I conceive) capable of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetation as man was. And if he be called or reckoned an Angel or Prince of Darkneſs it is either,</p>
            <p>Becauſe, he liveth in the dark, as unto the apprehenſions of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Love towards himſelf, or,</p>
            <p>Becauſe, he doth chiefly ſince his Apoſtacy (being an utter Enemy to all the Image of God which is Light and Purity) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118718:6"/>to act and bring forth in the conceptions and converſations of men, ſuch abominable things as are called Works of Darkneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12, 13. ſuch as rioting and drunkenneſs, chambering and wantonneſs, ſtrife and envy; theſe may well be called Works of Darkneſs, for they are acted of men againſt that light they have in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and they are not willing to be ſeen in the practice thereof. But leaving of ſuch particular verbal obſervations, I will proceed to ſhew what the Apoſtle would have to be ſummarily taught from his apprehenſions and expreſſions upon that myſtery of deceit; in order whereunto I have for method and rule ſake, reſolved upon theſe enſuing Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctrine</hi> 1. That when Satan ſindeth a people living ſo ſtrictly and exactly in that light and power they have received, that he cannot prevail upon them by temptations of a groſs ſort, ſuch as are thoſe provocations unto open profareneſs, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs and pride, and the like, then he concludeth upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way by ſuiting himſelf for their diſpoſitions and capacities, if it be to transform himſelf into the likeneſs of God, and as it were to act the part of God ſeemingly under fair pretences, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly words, ſelf-denying actions, righteous converſations, and the like; that ſo by this means he may at laſt inſinuate himſelf into their underſtandings and affections; for he will not leave any thing unattempted, that may (if it be but in probability of it) ſerve to ſeduce a poor people, eſpecially ſuch as are neareſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lamb, deſiring to follow him whitherſoever he goeth. This maketh him come forth thus diſguiſed, as an Angel of Light, to work, through a myſterious vail, under which he would not be ſeen to be himſelf, upon the hearts and mindes of thoſe that he can by no other means overcome; for I am perſwaded this way of working is very much contrary to his Apoſtatized condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as it may appear in that he doth ſo little and hath ſo ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome uſed it; for when do we hear or reade of any age, if it were not that of <hi>Christ</hi> and his Apoſtles, wherein he was ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated, and did ſo boldly and audaciouſly act in this nature, except this of our time among thoſe poor beguiled wretches cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Quakers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This in a general diſcovery is that diſguiſed angelical and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118718:6"/>deceitfull operation of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> there ſpoken of by <hi>Paul,</hi> and which is now ſo much practiced by that Enemy of poor mankinde: yet ſeeing in what I am going about (the Lord is my witneſs) I intend the real good and clear underſtanding both of Truth and Falſhood, that ſo the one may be avoided, the other by all poſſible endeavours attained unto, and kept faſt by all people, and that as freely as I can from all manner of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice or heart-burning unto thoſe people, whoſe ſad and ever to be lamented condition hath moved my heart, hand, pen and all to this Paper; Although I have had (I confeſs) great and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold occaſions offered by them unto my poor, weak and ſinfull heart, by reaſon of their clamorous railing Letters and unjuſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations and charges, to have carried it forth into paſſion and harſh language towards them; and I have been ſorely tempted herewith ſeveral times, but the Lord (to the praiſe of his grace I ſpeak it) hath had mercy on me, and hath carried me above theſe temptations, and hath filled my heart with moderation and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, pitying their condition; and I am ſo far perſwaded of his love, that as he hath drawn forth and enlarged my heart to diſcover what I know concerning this matter, ſo he will in his truth and wiſdom guide me untill I have finiſhed, that neither gall of bitterneſs or any manner of revenge or ſelf appear at all in my words or expreſſions, concerning thoſe enſlaved creatures. And thus truſting to my God, and deſiring his holy and bleſſed aſſiſtance, withall intending a publick good, as I ſpake, I have thought beſt for the more clear manifeſtation of this myſtery of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity, to lay it down in ſeveral particular operations and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings according to my knowledg and underſtanding therein, and that obſerving altogether this order:
<list>
                  <item>1. Laying down the Myſtery or Work it ſelf.</item>
                  <item>2. Shewing what ground or colour Satan findeth out for the ſame in Scripture-words and inſtance.</item>
                  <item>3. In giving my own once uncomfortable experience and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony unto the ſaid Works.</item>
                  <item>4. To give in the way and manner of the teaching of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God to each particular in its place.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Although I am ignorant whether the Lord hath drawn forth the heart of any man in all the Regions of our Goſpel-profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118718:7"/>to write and ſpeak againſt this ſubtle archievment of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ</hi> or no, yet in this me thinks I am conſcientious to my ſelf, that there is hardly a man to be found that hath been ſo much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared as I have been, and delivered through divine love, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof I am beſt able to give the trueſt demonſtration, and for ought that I do at the preſent know this might be one end in the Lord to ſuffer me to wade ſo far in that troubled Sea, that I might afterward give an experimental teſtimony of the great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and trouble thereof, for the ſake of others, that they may learn to beware the ſame danger, <hi>Faelix quem faciunt aliena pericula cautum, Praemonitus praemunitus.</hi> If <hi>Dives</hi> being in torment (parabolically) ſeemeth to diſcover ſo much natural affection as to deſire his brethrens timely admonition and caution, it would be a ſtrange thing and miſerable, if any of the Lords ſervants ſhould want what ſuch a one ſhould have, while the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teacheth us to be, <hi>Alteri quod nobis,</hi> that to another which we would have another be to us. Theſe conſiderations make me willing to uſe my beſt endeavour for a full and profitable unfold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this ſecret work, with all poſſible plainneſs and fitted lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage for the meaneſt capacities, and ſo to return unto particular Demonſtrations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Demonstrat.</hi> 1. It muſt needs be the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Antichrist</hi> and deluſion,<note place="margin">A miſinformation of the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> that doth miſinform the heart, and ſo maketh it judg amiſs of things, for the ſoul being poſſeſſed with an underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any thing, accordingly diſcovereth it ſelf, while it is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and void of hypocriſie, and by reaſon of this wrong informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it proceedeth to wrong judgment, diſowning and condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what it ought to own and approve; and contrariwiſe, own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and approving what it ought to diſown and condemn. This baſe deceit doth <hi>Antichrist</hi> bring forth in the hearts of thoſe people called the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who are ſo clearly miſtaken in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they call evil good, and good evil, knowing not what they ſay, nor whereof they affirm; they do judg the ways, act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and practices of all people to be abominable, Antichriſtian, and unjuſt, except their own, and above all people do they cry out againſt, and diſown ſuch, who by the world are reproached, and diſowned, as the Church and Diſciples of CHRIST.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118718:7"/>
            <p> But I need not ſpeak of the miſtake in them, in order to other people, while I have ſo clear a teſtimony thereof in relation to my ſelf, for however I may be ignorant what is in the hearts of ſome others, yet I cannot be altogether ignorant of my own, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſpirit that is in man knoweth his heart, and manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the hidden things thereof, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.</p>
            <p>I have been charged and accuſed by Letters from ſeveral of them;</p>
            <p>Firſt, of Hypocriſie;<note place="margin">My own firſt charge was Hypocriſie.</note> now the Lord knoweth, and I my ſelf know, how hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a thing hypocriſie, diſſimulation, and double dealing both with God and man, hath ever been unto me, even in thoſe days while I lived onely in the light, life, power and gifts of the firſt <hi>Adam.</hi> And therefore, knowing my own heart in this thing to be free, I do clearly apprehend them to be miſtaken, and to judg with unrighteous judgment, which a knowing man will confeſs to be of <hi>Antichrist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, they charge and accuſe me for acting againſt my own conſcience, meaning my living,<note place="margin">For acting againſt my own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> dwelling and preaching conſtantly unto a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar people in a publick meeting-place, this they ſay is againſt my own light and convictions of heart, as though they knew my conſcience better than my ſelf; hereby do I ſee again they are acted through deluſion and miſtake, for they urge that with confidence (ſuch as it is) which I can with much more confidence and boldneſs in the Lord, deny and juſtifie the the contrary hereof; for I do with much peace of minde, and that in the Lord (I bleſs him for it) preach that part of the Goſpel which I have received from him, unto this people, with much tenderneſs of affections and out-goings of my heart towards them, as they are my witneſſes; and it is noted and obſerved by this people generally (I do not ſay, how much more by my ſelf,) that I am carried forth to ſpeak unto them far more powerfully from time to time, and more prevailingly upon their affections and underſtandings, ſince I did freely, knowingly and conſiderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in publick manner renounce Tyths, than ever I did before. Now let any ſober man obſerve by what power theſe creatures are acted while they charge me with doing this againſt my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118718:8"/>and light, ſeeing the Lord qualifieth me more and more for the work, and attends it with greater bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they charge me with being an Enemy to the Lords people, meaning themſelves (I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) I confeſs they are the Lords creatures,<note place="margin">To be an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to the Lords people.</note> but how to call them in their preſent Apoſtacy and deluſion, properly his people, I know not, yet as they are his creatures I hate them not, for I have not ſo learned <hi>Christ,</hi> but rather to love and to deſire to do good in my place unto all, but to ſhew the world their great deluſion and miſtake in this, I have had ſomething from divine grace always working in me (while I was not under this temptation of theirs) an holy tenderneſs, and honorable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto all that which I could diſcern to be the work of the Father through his Son upon the hearts of any people in whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever form they walked. And I am perſwaded the Churches of mine acquaintance in all countreys where I have been to ſee &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the work of God among them, will witneſs on my behalf in this thing, for this thing they did and I hope do ſtill love &amp; tender me, although I never did walk with any of them in their Church order, ſince I came forth of Legaliſm. Yet notwithſtanding I am able to ſpeak this truth from my own heart, which is better known unto me, than any of them, and beſide the teſtimony of the Churches wherein I am bold, theſe poor beguiled creatures through that myſterious ſpirit of deceit and lying in them do lay this thing unto my charge.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they charge me that I never paſſed the new birth, but am onely acted by my natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts to all that I do. If it be ſo,<note place="margin">Not paſſing the new birth.</note> I wiſh all natural men were ſo acted too, that they might bear witneſs unto what they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm. Although I do know that a natural man may make a very large progreſs in a Goſpel profeſſion and converſation, yet I am through the rich grace and love of God ſhed abroad in my heart, able to give a perfect and experimental diſcovery unto ſuch, who are able to judg thereof, by that one Spirit we have both recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, of that new birth or creation in <hi>Christ,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; for otherwiſe there could be but little ſound peace or joy in my ſoul, ſeeing I know very well, how little ſatisfactory the utmoſt attainments in the firſt creation would be unto me, that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118718:8"/>have ſo much knowledg in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> if my knowledg were meerly notional and formal; and beſides I hope there hath been long ago, and many times, good ſatisfaction given unto moſt of the Lords ſervants, with whom there hath been mutual gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings and receivings of teſtimonies and manifeſtations, in that one common grace of God in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to the rejoycing of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hearts and the building up of one another in that grace and faith wherein we were called. But were it ſo that I lived in a Wilderneſs, and all the men in the World were unſatisfied and ignorant in this thing, ſo that I my ſelf were knowingly ſatisfied, and that upon good grounds, it would be ſufficient for my faith, and hopes of an eternal weight of glory at the righteous revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Judg of Heaven and Earthe and therefore let this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Charge prove a blank for all uſes, beſide proving its original to be a ſpirit of <hi>Anitchriſt</hi> and deluſion.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, they charge me with back-ſliding, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in their ſenfe, they may do ſo juſtly,<note place="margin">Back-ſliding.</note> For it is the great mercy of God unto me I was delivered from under thoſe grievous delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and temptations unto which they are yet in bondage; but that which they call back-ſliding is my retuming back unto my God, and my holding faſt and contending for that faith which I had once received, <hi>Jude</hi> 2. according to the minde of the Lord diſcovered, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6. concerning the holding faſt of confidence, of rejoycing, of hope firm unto the end. Thus you may ſee that which they reckon my judgment is my mercy, and that which they call my back-ſliding is my owning and receiving my former principles and teachings according to truth. Now let him that hath an eye ſee, and who ſo hath an heart let him judg; whence cometh this great miſtake, unjuſt judgment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and when ye have well weighed theſe things ye ſhall finde it cannot ſtand with the honor of God to teach a people things which are not true, as to my comfort and their ſhame doth clearly appear, notwithſtanding they pretend and ſay they were made to write theſe things as from the Lord.</p>
            <p>Theſe five acouſations are moſt that I have received from any of them, and I ſuppoſe the moſt they were prompt with all from that ſpirit of deceit, for had there been any more given in unto them, it is like they would have diſcloſed it as well as this:</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:118718:9"/>
            <p> And it is not onely to myſelf they write thus, but unto moſt people of any note or quality above others, eſpecially amongſt thoſe that make any profeſſion of the ways of the Lord, differing from the men of the world, as I hear by ſeveral, and by their own confeſſion to myſelf formerly. And I would have all the world obſerve, how they write with abundance of railing and clamorous words, and unjuſt accuſations, as you have heard me prove; and their language is much after the ſame ſort, unto whom they write; which maketh me note that they are exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary one to another in their writing, taking up the ſame form of words, and it teacheth me alſo to conſider how Satan is no Nig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard (as we ſay) of his skill and power, for they pretend they are abundantly filled up with matter of that nature, as though they could never vent themſelves of it all.</p>
            <p>Now I have laid down the work or deceit it ſelf in this nature, I will return unto my ſecond Rule,<note place="margin">The ſecond Rule to find the colour in the Scripture</note> which to finde out where Satan doth colour over and blinde this fallacy with ſome Scripture words or inſtances.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for their railing and reviling language they will not own it as ſuch, but count it a ſharp rebuking and reptoving men, as though they had ſome ſpecial authority or power of truth in them acting of them thereunto, and ſo Satan doth hide this deceit under that command which <hi>Paul</hi> giveth <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. where he biddeth him rebuke the <hi>Cretians</hi> and others ſharply; and <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.15. he biddeth him rebuke with all authority; and they obſerve the Prophet <hi>Nathans</hi> coming unto <hi>David</hi> and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Thou art the man:</hi> and why may not they, who ſay they are ſent of the Lord as <hi>Nathan</hi> was, ſpeak in that manner unto men, be they Rulers or others, ſeeing that God is no reſpecter of perſons? and beſides this, Satan cannot be ignorant of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Christs</hi> reproving <hi>Peter,</hi> when he called him Satan. Theſe and ſuch like Examples carry out the deceit very fairly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch who are ignorant of his devices.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as for their charging men with hypocriſie, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding, and being but onely in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> (for they judg all beſide themſelves to be ignorant of the new-birth be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo well gifted and taught of God) and the like, it proceedeth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118718:9"/>from that blindneſs which <hi>Antichist</hi> hath caſt in upon their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, from whence they cannot chuſe but ſpeak evil of the things they know not, <hi>Jude</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>And ſo judging all men to be in this eſtate, they take the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of CHRIST in calling them Hypocrites, as he did the Scribes and Phariſes, and pronouncing Woes againſt them as they do againſt many people and places, as they have told me themſelves how they have declared Judgment and Woes againſt a place called <hi>Kendall</hi> in the North, I know not well in what County it is; but I will onely ſay this one word unto ye O people of <hi>Kendall,</hi> if it be for your holding faſt unto the faith of the Goſpel, and your bold courage to withſtand <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and all his myſterious actings of unrighteouſneſs, that you are ſo vilified and diſowned by them, it may be your grace and glory: but if it be through a kinde of wilfulneſs and ſpirit of malice, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge and bitterneſs againſt the poor creatures that you are ſo car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried againſt them, I commend you not. Therefore look unto it. O what a vail or cover hath Satan got himſelf here under the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of <hi>Christ</hi> himſelf? Yet let all people underſtand, that ſuch as <hi>Christ</hi> did call Hypocrites and his Enemies, were ſo indeed, as he proved by long experience; but ſuch as theſe creatures call ſo are the moſt precious and eminent and faithfull friends that the Lord hath amongſt all the ſons of men; therefore now judg of the deluſion.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the third Rule of diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing this ſecret, which is my own experience in order to this particular,<note place="margin">The third Rule in Demonſtr. 1. is my own experience.</note> while I lay under theſe temptations.</p>
            <p>Experence I have in this thing ſufficiently, although I was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver carried much forth into any ſuch practice; for although I have had many movings and ſtirrings in my heart to write to ſome particular men, with all poſſible haiſh language and unjuſt accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations (as I now ſee) yet the Lord did by one ſecret means or other prevent me; onely once I wrote unto ſeveral people with abundance of bitter expreſſions, and yet all exact Scripture-lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; and as I gave an hint before how they have told me, that ſometimes when they are made to write in this nature, they are ſo ſiled up with matter and phraſes of Scripture for their purpoſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118718:10"/>that they know not how to make an end; even ſo it was with me at that time when I wrote that Letter, for I do at this time perfectly remember that I told them the very next time I ſaw them, how I was made to write to ſuch a people at ſuch a time, and in ſuch a place, ſuch and ſuch things, and I ſaid I was ſo fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and the Scriptures were ſo tumbled in upon me, that I could have dictated faſt enough for four Pens to have writ, and I think I left three parts of four that were as it were laid open before me to pick and chuſe, unwrit. Elſe beſide this Letter I do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that ever I wrote any of that nature, but I wrote ſeveral Letters to whole Congregations and private perſons in high ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions in Scripture-phraſe, (for it is the Devils policy to keep cloſe to that) and in high commendation of that diſpenſation (as I then judged it and called it) of God, with many encouraging Arguments unto the people to whom I writ to wait and look for that glorious way and diſcovery of divine light and power, to be brought forth among all the children of the Moſt High, O My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery <hi>Babylon!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, we will make known the very truth of this deluſion, by comparing theſe kinde of actings and teachings of the heart,<note place="margin">The fourth Rule in Demonſtr. 1. is the teaching of the Spirit of God.</note> with thoſe that the Spirit of Truth in the Lord was and is wont to bring forth in the ſouls of his people in this particular thing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whereas theſe people are miſtaken in their judgment, and made to accuſe and condemn people for what they ought not, you ſhall finde the Spirit of God teaching his ſervants in another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, according to the promiſe of being guided by that Spirit into all truth, and like that which the Lord maketh concerning his people, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> They ſhall <hi>diſcern between the righteous and the wicked, between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not,</hi> If any ſhall ſay this was a promiſe God made with ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular men, as the Prophets, or <hi>Christ,</hi> or his Apoſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> You ſhall finde in reading that place, that it was ſpoken to all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord upon that great acceptation the Lord had of them upon the account of their meeting often together, and ſpeaking one to another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And beſides you ſhall finde the Apoſtle 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. writing unto all ſorts of Gods people, and telling them
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118718:10"/>
               <hi>v.</hi> 27. that they have received ſuch an holy anointing from the Spirit of the Lord, which ſhould teach them all things, for in it there was no Lie, and therefore they needed not that any man ſhould teach them. And furthermore, if you do but obſerve, you ſhall ſee when any poor ſinners heart is called into and filled with the knowledg of the love of God, as it is given forth through <hi>Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A deſcription of the new birth.</note> and is engaged in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and affections to the Lord, that every ſuch ſinner thus converted is preſently able to judg ſuch a people to be indeed in truth the children of God, and he is likewiſe able to judg on the other ſide, that all ſuch who are not brought in with the love and deſire of their ſouls, and in that love made one with his ſervants, are yet in the firſt eſtate and ſo ſtrangers to that diſpenſation or covenant of free grace in <hi>Christ.</hi> Although this alteration or change be but of a ſhort time; for he is become a new creature, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. New as well in his judgment &amp; apprehenſions of the differing eſtates of the firſt and ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> as well as new in his practice and converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.15. For though the natural man diſcerneth not theſe things yet conſequently he that is baptized with that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and holy anointing of the Spirit doth know and apprehend them, for he judgeth all things, although he himſelf or rather his new birth be no rightly judged of any man not under that divine operation. 2. Whereas they are filled up with railing harſh and clamorous language, it is but what is incident to ſuch a miſ-lead people, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.4 5. 2 <hi>Tim,</hi> 3.4. I finde here when once a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are drawn from ſound Doctrine they may be brought to any thing; but however they are continually acted thus againſt thoſe whom they apprehend do oppoſe them and their deceits; yet it is ſaid of the Lord JESUS CHRIST, <hi>Jude</hi> 9 that when he was diſputing with the Devil about the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> he durſt not bring any railing accuſation againſt him, but ſaid, <hi>The Lord rebuke thee.</hi> Yet theſe creatures do adventure to do what <hi>Christ</hi> would not. Moreover we finde what counſel <hi>Paul</hi> giveth <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24, 25 28. The ſervant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle unto all men, apt to teach, patient, in meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs inſtructing them that oppoſe themſelves, if God peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will give them repentance to the acknowledging of the truth,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118718:11"/>and that they may recover themſelves out of the ſnare of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil who are taken captive at his will; and <hi>Paul</hi> in his 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19. biddeth him that he ſhould not receive any accuſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an Elder, except it were before two or three witneſſes, and yet theſe people when they receive no accuſation at all before any witneſs do through the imagination of their own hearts or rather the ſuggeſtions of Satan, ſend moſt railing and unjuſt ones againſt ſuch who are not onely Elders but Pillars of the Truth in the Church of <hi>Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, in as much as they ſay (and I know it is true) that they are filled up with matter, Scripture and expreſſions: yet note theſe two differences,</p>
            <p n="1">1. When they are made thus to write abundantly unto men, charging and accuſing of them without knowledg or truth, they are not able to juſtifie and make good their wrongfull accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but when any man is moved of the Lord to write unto a man or people, telling them in love and according to truth of their tranſgreſſions or failings, he is able to juſtifie what he hath writ, and to declare the truth of things more fully, and that with ſo much power and majeſty, that it doth beget an acknowledgment commonly, or filence in the heart of the tranſgreſſor: but when they write eſpecially unto people of ſound judgment, and well grounded and eſtabliſhed in the faith of <hi>Christ,</hi> it is ſo far from begetting any ſilence or convictions upon them, that it doth rather diſcover it ſelf to be what it is indeed, deluſion and good for nothing but to be returned back and ſtrongly reſiſted in the Name and power of the Lord,</p>
            <p n="2">2. This kinde of writing (I know what I ſpeak by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) is with ſuch a kinde of lording and vain-glorying over the eſtate of ſuch unto whom it is written, as though they were not worthy to be writ unto, I can hardly tell how to expreſs this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit in words, it is with ſo much undervaluing and vilifying of men, that in cannot match it ſelf with the teachings of God in this kinde; but when the ſoul is moved hereunto from that power as it cometh purely from God, it is mixed with ſo much love and tenderneſs, it remembers it ſelf and remembers anothers conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it doth make anothers condition its own, and its own ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſo it was wont to work in the hearts of the ſervants of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118718:11"/>
               <hi>Christ,</hi> as we may find by <hi>Pauls</hi> words when he ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1, 2. Brethren, if a man be overtaken in a fault, ye which are ſpiritual reſtore ſuch a one in the ſpirit of meekneſs, conſidering thy ſelf, leſt thou alſo be tempted.</p>
            <p>And as for that fulneſs of knowledg and words, and the like, which is a moſt ſtrong and prevailing deluſion, and carrieth more the heart of a creature away than any other thing I know as yet manifeſted, whither it be the heart of him in whom it is already conceived, or of another that ſhall once clearly know it to be ſo; for to ſee one as it were yeſterday not able to write or ſay any thing although to a mean capacity, to be able this day to write in ſuch a large manner, (as I my ſelf know ſome) it begetteth abundance of admiration and ſilence for a time in the beholders, eſpecially ſuch who are of ſmall knowledg and underſtanding in myſterious things. But let not this blinde any man, you ſhall finde it nothing but deluſion in conſidering theſe Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars:</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is like a lightning from the Sky, come and gone in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time; for at another time (as they confeſs themſelves) they cannot do ſo much if it were to gain the world, and yet at that very inſtant of time, while this deceitfull power worketh them thereunto, they muſt do ſo, nay, if it be to riſe of their beds, and if they be not very obſervative hereunto they ſhall be made to ſuffer moſt unheard of troubles, agonies and paſſions, as they have often told me, untill they do yield obedience unto that wicked ſpirit, and then they apprehend themſelves at very much peace for a time, untill Satan have a deſire to make uſe of them again. Now that fulneſs of knowledg and words which are wrought in the ſoul from the power of truth, is more laſting and durable, it is the owners to day, and to morrow, the Lord doth not uſe to ſteal away his truth and his knowledg from his ſervants in this manner: but if they ſee good and juſt ground of writing or ſpeaking once, they can do ſo twice or thrice or oftner; and I have this thing to bleſs the Lord for in a ſpecial manner. I cannot ſay that I do remember the time, ſince I was in any noted and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable meaſure endowed with the gifts of God through his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son, that ever I did want matter or expreſſions either to write or ſpeak in publick or private to many or to few, but have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118718:12"/>always found my ſelf abundantly furniſhed with ſome kinde of experimental knowledg in order to one particular truth or other whereof I was to deliver my ſelf, that I needed not to go and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate things, by long digeſted ſerious meditations, readings, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and the like; for in my apprehenſions it is very eaſie for a man to divulge that which he is truly and ſoundly taught of God, as the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.2, 3. That Life and Light which we have ſeen and heard declare we unto you. But I muſt confeſs that I do very well know it to be a difficult thing for ſuch who are untaught in that thing they are to communicate unto others, while they muſt be digging for it out of earthly mines.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Me thinks if theſe creatures were moved and neceſſitated in this nature from the power and Spirit of God to write and ſpeak ſuch ſharp things in ſuch a terrible and threatning manner unto particular ſouls or people, that their writing and ſpeaking would be of great power and prevalency with them, that they ſhould be convinced by it, and ſhould not be able to defie it as deluſion and madneſs.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Nathan</hi> was ſent in ſuch a particular manner from the Lord unto <hi>David,</hi> it preſently convinced him, and when <hi>Jonah</hi> was ſent to <hi>Nineveh,</hi> with that ſad news from God, they were preſently convinced by it, but I ſee no conviction, or ſubjection, or fear, or love, or any ſuch thing wrought by it, it being like the chirping of Birds in the air, for matter of weight and worth: which maketh me judg (and ſo may any man elſe that hath his judgment rectified by divine Light) that all this fulneſs of words and expreſſions, as I have mentioned, are meerly ſuggeſted and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired into their hearts by <hi>Antichrist</hi> diſguiſed.</p>
            <p>This ſhall ſuffice for the Examination and Trial of the firſt Demonſtration, and I will now proceed to a ſecond.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Demonſtration of this deceit is thus to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <p>It muſt needs be the power of <hi>Antichrist</hi> working through deceit, that robbeth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priveth the ſoul of all thoſe former ways and means wherein the Lord did work faith,<note place="margin">Domonſtr. 2. is a robbing the ſoul of its former knowledg, &amp;c.</note> knowledg and enjoyments in the hearts of his children, nay, and which robbeth them of all thoſe former excellent things which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118718:12"/>were brought forth in them by the power of Truth: and as it ſtealeth away all thoſe ways wherein God hath manifeſted his love and grace to them, ſo it hath deprived them of the uſe of thoſe ways of walking wherein they have manifeſted any love or obedience to God, ſo that they are people bereaved of all things of this nature, and they reckon it their happineſs and their perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſo to be, and I have heard them complain exceedingly that they were not wholly taken off ſuch things, but they did finde (as they were wont to ſay) their hearts hanging upon old diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ways, diſcoveries, and the like. All theſe things they ſay muſt be burnt up in them and deſtroyed, and becauſe there is ſo much hereof remaining, they underſtand it is that they are brought into ſo great ſufferings, agonies and paſſions, which they reckon the fiery work, going on to perfect what is amiſs in them.</p>
            <p>They eſteem alſo the more the heart is brought off from the meditations and conſiderations of Gods former dealings, and the more negligent it is become in hearing, reading praying, or any ſuch heavenly and their own once exerciſe, the more pure and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it is become, and they ſay if it were ſo with them, they could altogether ceaſe from theſe things, it would be well with them, waiting onely for that great and mighty power which they ſay is of God, to act them unto any ſuch conſideration or meditation, reading, praying, or the like; for they think that all that acted them hereunto formerly was the power of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and therefore being not of <hi>Christ,</hi> it ought to be denied and thrown away as an abominable thing. Thus in brief they are acted in judgment and practice in this particular; here is the work or my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious deceit, let us now proceed to our ſecond Rule which is to finde where Satan hath Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and inſtance to help himſelf, and hide his deceit in this thing.<note place="margin">The ſecond Rule Demonſt. 2. is the Scripture and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then, whereas they exſpect and deſire the dying and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing of all ſuch former ways of God to them, Satan covereth himſelf in theſe words, <hi>Iſai</hi> 65.17. Behold I create new Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and a new Earth, and the former ſhall not be remembred nor come into my minde. And that of <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17, 18. Lo, old things are done away, and all things are become new, and all things are of God: here is a deep and dangerous covert that he hath got.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:118718:13"/>
            <p> Secondly, for the giving over all thoſe practices and exerciſes of the ſoul, unleſs it be when they are ſo moved, as they ſay, you ſhall finde Satan coloring over this buſineſs very fairly with that inſtance and writing of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 3.7, 8. in ſaying that all which was once his gain he now counted loſs for <hi>Christ,</hi> for the ſake of whoſe excellent knowledg he did deſire to count all his former righteouſneſs but loſs and dung. A dangerous place while it is ſo miſtaken. And there is a ſaying of <hi>Christs</hi> own mouth which through the deceitfull unfolding thereof by <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ,</hi> doth much blinde them, <hi>John</hi> 4 21, 22, 23. The hour cometh and now is, ſaith <hi>Christ,</hi> that neither in this Mountain, nor eke at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhall the Father be worſhipped, for he is a Spirit, and he will be worſhipped in ſpirit and truth.</p>
            <p>And beſides theſe, they are beguiled by the inſtance of <hi>Pauls</hi> converſion, and the command that <hi>Christ</hi> gave the Twelve to go unto <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and there to ſtay untill they ſhould receive ſuch a meaſure of the ſpirit as is there mentioned <hi>Acts</hi> 2. from the beginning to <hi>v.</hi> 20. together with the miſ-apprehending of <hi>Joels</hi> Propheſie in that place.</p>
            <p>No queſtion if Satan had need he could finde out more hiding places than theſe, but theſe I am ſure he maketh great uſe of, as I my ſelf do very well know.</p>
            <p>My own experience in this thing maketh me ſpeak what I do, for had I received theſe things by relation onely, I ſhould have judged it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true. But I will ſhew plainly and orderly the thoughts of my own heart about this thing,<note place="margin">The third Rule in Demonſtr. 2. my own experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> while I was ſo much under thoſe dark clouds.</p>
            <p>Although I was not wholly deprived or taken off my former experiences of the ways of Gods dealing with me, neither was I made wholly to ceaſe from the uſe of thoſe ways of manifeſting love and obedience to my God, which I had lived in and owned of long time before; yet I reckoned it my weakneſs and imperfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that I was not, and although I did without any intermiſſion continue ſpeaking and praying with my people in publick, ſo that they perceived not any thing at all, yet I was exceedingly tempted to have denied it and given it over, and I was wont to complain very much of the hardneſs of my own heart that I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118718:13"/>would not yield unto that thing, being, in my then apprehenſion, utterly condemned, onely there was a mighty power of God keeping that little ſpark of light alive in me by his own breathing upon it, and I was not aware, that I might ſay, Surely God was in this place and I knew it not, for I am perſwaded, if the Lord had ſuffered me to have been overcome in this temptation, I had been wholly carried away as the leſt are, and had been to this hour, for ought I know, in bondage with them; but the wiſdom and love of God which kept me is too deep to be ſpoken of in this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, onely I tell all the world, that I am not able to tell them, what a mighty warfare I did undergo many days and weeks about that thing, but <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel who was moſt worthy had the preeminence in that duel, all honor and praiſe be given unto him for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>And note this thing further, while I lay under this temptation I did finde ſome power denying me to uſe thoſe gifts and graces I had, ſo that although they were alive in me, and me thinks I could have prayed and have ſpoke as I was wont, yet there was ſomething turning me aſide, and as it were forbidding me, which I did moſt of all hearken unto and yield unto for the greateſt part, except it were on the firſt days among my people in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</p>
            <p>Thus I do well remember it was with me in order to this deceit, as I may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo call it, becauſe I know it to be ſo through a moſt powerfull manifeſtation of Truth.<note place="margin">Rule 4. in Demonſtr. 2. is the reaching of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God.</note>I am now come unto the</p>
            <p>Fourth Rule which I obſerve in my method, and that is the way of the teaching of the Spirit of God in Truth in order to theſe things and Scriptures, whereby Satan hath beguiled the hearts of poor creatures.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in as much as they reckon it their perfection and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to be deprived of all, as you have heard. The Spirit of God doth neither ſo act nor ſo teach, but on the contrary bringeth forth more and more ways and manifeſtations and freſh experiences of his love into the hearts of his people; and <hi>David</hi> was glad many times to remember the antient loving kindneſſes of God, and becauſe of the excellency and comforts that ariſe from much
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118718:14"/>knowledg and remembrance of Gods love and formermercies, the Apoſtle prayeth ſo as he did for the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> that they might increaſe and be filled up with all knowledg and ſpiritual under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſtrengthened with all might, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.9, 10, 11. They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to become fools, and to be made weak, and I know not what, And they had one expreſſion which did ſtumble me a great while, and it was this, That the beſt things that ever we received from God, mentioning knowledg and faith and high enjoyments, as I well remember yet their words, muſt be burnt up and deſtroyed; this I thought to be a very ſtrange kinde of language, and indeed ſo it is, when it is compared with that of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7, 8.9. where the Holy Ghoſt commandeth the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord to be carefull to ſeek after the increaſings of grace in their hearts, and telleth them, that while ſuch things ſhall increaſe, it will make them be fruitfull; but if they ſhall lack theſe things, it will cauſe them to be blinde, that they ſhall not be able to ſee far off; and truly ſo are theſe people that are thus miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, for they are ſo far from being able to ſee things a far off, that they cannot ſee the preſent horrible and deviliſh deluſions under which they live, and this is the juſt recompence of reward for ſuch creatures, who will negligently uſe thoſe gifts and graces they have once received: It is no marvel they ſay, they have loſt all their former experiences and enjoyments, and the like, for CHRIST taught ſo much in the Parable of the Talents, where we may learn, that idle ſluggiſh people who will not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their Talents ſhall have them taken away from them. The underſtanding of this moved the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to give ſuch a ſtrict charge unto his Scholar <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13, 14, 15, 16. Till I come, give attendance to reading, to exhortation, to do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, not neglecting the gift that is in thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and meditate upon theſe things, and give thy ſelf wholly unto them, that thy profiting may appear unto all; and further ſaith he, Take heed unto thy ſelf, and unto thy Dectrine, continuing in them, for in ſo doing thou ſhalt both ſave thy ſelf and them that hear thee.</p>
            <p>Here we finde the Holy Ghoſt judgeth it meet and convenient that all care and diligence ſhould be uſed both in reading, exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another, and in the exerciſing of thoſe graces where with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118718:14"/>the Lord had <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dowed the ſoul, that ſo they might be kept alive: but theſe beguiled wretches pretend, they muſt not reade or ſpeak a good word to one another, or do any thing of this nature, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they can finde, as they pretend, themſelves moved thereunto of the Spirit, as it were by ſome extraordinary and immediate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation or inſpiration: but the Spirit of the Lord teacheth his ſervants to know that it is always the minde of the Lord, that thoſe meaſures and proportions of grace which he hath beſtowed ſhould beuſed to the utter moſt of their extent<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and it is the nature of the grace of God manifeſſed in CHRIST to enable and quicken the ſoul for a conſtant courſe of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and holy exercitations,<note place="margin">A deſcription of ſpiritual prayer.</note> and therefore the Spirit of CHRIST is called a quickning Spirit; and hence the Apoſtle biddeth the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to pray always with all manner of prayer and ſupplication in the Spirit, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.18. that is, with that life, power and ſtrength which remains in the heart, from that meaſure and operation of divine grace or love already received, and ſaith he in this place, Watch thereunto with all perſeverance. And again, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.17. Pray without ceaſing, 19. Quench not the Spirit. Theſe teachings you ſee of the Spirit of God are altogether contrary unto this negligence in them, and a vain deceitfull waiting for a power, as they call it, if it be ſo they have no power, the greater and more miſerable is their loſs. I ſaid before, that when I lay under theſe kinde of Temptations my ſelf, that I did not finde my power gone, but me thoughts I could have prayed, and have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at ſome other times, yet me thinks my will and deſire was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cold thereunto, and I found ſomething diſſwading of me from the uſing of my gifts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And as they are thus deprived of all abilities, as they ſay themſelves, for reading and praying, and the like: ſo they ſay they have no freedom to ſpeak, admoniſh or diſcourſe about any thing, that they may glorifie the Lord, or do good unto others; but rather ſay, that they muſt ceaſe from their own words, and wait till they have ſome immediate ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or working of the Spirit, as they fancy it, for that purpoſe alſo.</p>
            <p>How contrary this is unto the minde of the Lord, you ſhall ſee 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. Be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon to preach, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118718:15"/>rebuke, exhort with all long-ſuffering and doctrine; and as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. Hold faſt the form of ſound words, which thou haſt heard of me. And <hi>v</hi> 6, 7. Stir up the gift of God which is in thee, for God hath not given us the ſpirit of fear, but of power and love, and a ſound minde.</p>
            <p>Here is, you may eaſily finde, ſuch a vaſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> difference between both theſe ſorts of Teaching and Language, that without all diſpute, there can be but one of them the Language and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Christ,</hi> the other muſt needs be the Teaching and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious deceits of <hi>Antichrist.</hi> I will now end this, and proceed to a third Demonſtration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Demonst.</hi> 3. Which I gather from thoſe ſtrange and unheard of Paſſions and Agonies, thoſe great burthens and exercitations of body, in ſo much that they are ſometimes in Trances or Soun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and if they are not brought unto ſuch a ſtate of deadneſs as it were, yet they ſuffer moſt extreme. Tortures of body, that hath been viſible to me and ſeveral others many times, nay, ſo much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity that it maketh them roar out for very bitterneſs; and I do clearly judg that if the Lord did not limit the Devil in their behalf, as he did for <hi>Job,</hi> ſaying, Thou ſhalt not touch his life, it would be impoſſible for their concaves to hold their in wards, in thoſe violent motions, for they are made under thoſe Agonies to tremble and quake as though their fleſh muſt part from their bones and ligatures, like unto men in the ſtrongeſt fits of an Ague that ever you ſaw, as though they had ſeen <hi>Belſhazzars</hi> Viſion, <hi>Dan.</hi> 10. that made his knees ſmite one againſt another: in theſe ſtrange Paſſions they are exerciſed with ſo much heat (I know not of what ſort) that it maketh them cry out for Drink, and maketh them ſweat like men in moſt violent Feavers: now they call theſe Agonies the fiery Trial, and they fay it is the power of the Holy Ghoſt burning up and deſtroying their corruptions, and purifying them like Gold that is tried ſeven times in the fire: and that which is very ſtrange, when they are thus in the midſt of theſe extreme Shakings, Quakings, Trials, Roarings and Perplexities, that one would think there could not be more Torment upon the damned ſpirits than is upon them at the preſent, yet many times when they begin to come to their ſpeech, (for it falleth out often that they are not able to ſpeak for a long time) they will ſpeak
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118718:15"/>how much joy and pleaſure they have mixed with that Torment in ſuch an inſeparable manner as they themſelves expreſs, as heat and fire mixed together, that they could wiſh to be in it for ever and ever. This they call the drinking of the Cup, or the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going the Curſe and Wrath of God as <hi>Christ</hi> did, for here they ſpeak (to my underſtandings moſt blaſphemouſly) and ſay, they muſt be brought to ſuffer as <hi>Christ</hi> did, and to undergo as great a ſenſe of wrath as he did, when he cried out, <hi>My God, my God, why hast thou forſaken me?</hi> In a word, as far as ever I could underſtand their apprehenſions by their expreſſions in this laſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, I did judg this to be their deluſion, that they muſt ſuffer eternal burnings, beating the full weight of divine juſtice and wrath, as fully as though there never had been any <hi>Christ</hi> crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or acceptation of his Sacrifice, untill, as they ſay, there ſhould be no more left in them, but the pure ſeed of God in its own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect likeneſs; Thus reckoning as far as I am able to determine by their words, that upon this account they muſt be juſtified before the Lord.</p>
            <p>And I will here produce one grand Aſſertion more of theirs, and then let all the world try my Expoſition upon their Tenents, which is this, they ſay that condition or ſtate which is called in Scripture [Hell, or everlaſting Torment] or as we are wont to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand thoſe terms, a perpetual undergoing a ſenſe of the wrath of God, and his pure and full juſtice gone forth againſt all the ſins, tranſgreſſions and diſobediences of the creature; this they ſay is but a diſpenſation which ſhall end at ſuch a time, as that Burning and Torment of the ſoul and conſcience ſhall have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined it and brought it, into its former purity and likeneſs of God. Here is ſuch an Aſſertion which I think the world never ſaw or heard of before, you may ſpend your judgments upon it.</p>
            <p>In brevity I have thus given you the myſterious deceit it ſelf, now I come to the</p>
            <p>Second Rule, which is to ſhew you where Satan hides himſelf while he worketh thus upon them under Scripture lines and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.<note place="margin">The ſecond Rule in Demonſtr. 3. which is Scripture and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, for their ſore and cruel ſufferings they take the example of <hi>Christ,</hi> and think that they muſt ſuffer as he did, comparing his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118718:16"/>Agonies and their own together, and comparing his Croſs, and ſhame, and reproach, and cruel uſage by the people, and theirs together, and ſay, The Diſciple is not greater than his Maſter. And for that fiery Trial, as they call it, they are fed with a falſe gloſs upon the words of <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.2, 3. He is like a Refiners fire, and Fullers ſoap, and he ſhall ſit as a Refiner and Purifier of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that of <hi>John Baptist, Matth.</hi> 3.11. He ſhall baptize with the Holy Ghoſt and fire. And the words of <hi>Paul</hi> are very much abuſed unto them by the falſe interpretation of their Enemy, where he ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.13, 14, 15. that every mans work ſhall be revealed by fire, and the fire ſhall try every mans work of what ſort it is, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, for their Shakings, Quakings, Roarings, and the like, they have preſented unto them that ſtrange amazement of S. <hi>Paul</hi> at his Converſion. Alſo they are put in minde of many of <hi>Davids</hi> words in the <hi>Pſalms</hi> from place to place, where he ſpeaketh of the Heavens and the Earth trembling and falling down before the preſence of the Lord, as though they did ſee ſome mighty appearance of God at ſuch times; and then they are alſo put in minde how <hi>Davids</hi> heart was ſometimes wont to fail him for fear; and how he cried out ſometimes, all his bones were broken; and ſuch places and inſtances as theſe are abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly brought into their thoughts, when they are in their Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies or Shakings, as though they were prompt at the car with an audible voice: and they themſelves will confeſs, that before and after they were not able to ſpeak ſuch things; and generally, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be at ſuch times, you ſhall hardly gain a ſpeech of one ſort or another from them, in ſo much that ſometimes when I have deſired to have ſome fair reaſonings with them about ſome things, and found they would not, I have told them they were poſſeſſed of a dumb Devil as well as a railing Devil: for Satan is all upon extremes, he knoweth not the ſpirit of moderation; he told <hi>Christ</hi> he would give him all the World, not any competent part thereof. He kept <hi>Dives</hi> in the Parable that he ſhould not give any thing unto poor <hi>Laxarus.</hi> So he acteth theſe poor creatures upon extremes of one ſort or another, ſuch as they will be acted by, as he doth the wretched people of the world whom he overcometh with an extreme care and deſire after Covetouſneſs and Riches
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118718:16"/>that they never know any mean for their pains and increaſe, or how to make any good uſe of what they have, or elſe with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable deſire after profaneneſs, luſts and pleaſure, untill they have ſpent all upon their own folly and baſeneſs; ſo that it will be a very wonderfull thing to finde a man ſo free from theſe two extremes, that he ſhould know how to uſe the world as though he uſed it not, and to be content and praiſe the Lord if he do not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy things convenient.</p>
            <p>The third Rule is to ſhew the Word how much I can ſpeak unto this diſcovery out of mine own knowledg.<note place="margin">The third Rule in Demonſtr. 3.</note> Here I have leaſt to ſay of any thing whereunto I ſpake yet out of any knowledg more than by ſeeing and hearing of them, which I have ſeveral times, for that mighty hand and out ſtretched arm of the Lord under which I was then ſecretly kept, did not ſuffer me very much to be captivated in this nature; but I ſhought it was my unhappineſs that I was not, and it was great cauſe of trouble and unſpeakable ſorrow to me, and that which cauſed me to complain bitterly time after time, but they would tell me I muſt wait for it, and they ſaid they could believe for me, and they were confident I ſhould be a very glorious piece, and words to that effect very many; and this they would ſpeak with as much confidence, (as I did apprehend) as I can affirm that JESUS CHRIST is the Son of God: and therefore from hence I clearly ſee how they are befooled by <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist,</hi> for I am delivered out of the Temptation, and am now through divine Light and Love couſſelling all my generations to take heed of being overcome by the ſubtil ſtratagems of Satan, and likewiſe to beware of them, that they are his miniſters and ſervants, laboring through his deceitfull power and workings to bring other poor creatures in their own Region of Darkneſs and Valley of Death.</p>
            <p>Fourth Rule is the manner of the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God and his holy and bleſſed Spirit,<note place="margin">The fourth Rule in Demonſtr. 3.</note> about this thing.</p>
            <p>Firſt, where as they compare their ſufferings and Agonies with thoſe of CHRIST, and ſay, they muſt ſuffer the wrath of God, and the like, as he did, and yet reckon themſelves the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord; the Spirit of God will prove this to be a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118718:17"/>Lie and deluſion, becauſe that CHRIST ſuffered for his ſervants, and bore the wrath and curſe of God for them, and made ſatisfaction to his Fathers Law and Juſtice, in his own Bloud, and his Father was pleaſed to accept it, and ſo forth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is true of the damned, that they ſhall undergo the eternal wrath and juſtice of God upon their own conſciences, becauſe they refuſed to believe, love and obey the will of CHRIST concerning them, and made known in them, that ſo they might have had the benefit of that ſacrifice which <hi>Christ</hi> gave unto his Father for the ſins of others. But this is not true concerning the Lords faithfull ones, and that any judicious man may ſee by theſe enſuing teſtimonies of Scripture, <hi>Iſai</hi> 53. all that Chapter, Reade O ye people all this bleſſed Truth, and give your mindes to believe, and by believing it let your ſouls love him that did ſo much for the ſinfull ſons of men, and in loving of him give him up willing and chearfull obedience, which if you ſhall continue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end, your ſouls ſhall know in the teſtimony of Truth what this Scripture is worth, and you ſhall be able through the witneſs of the Holy Spirit of Promiſe to ſay and prove it is a moſt deviliſh Lie and deluſion to conceive that any who are one with God in <hi>Christ</hi> ſhall undergo the wrath of God in that manner that they ſpeak of, by this they make the Death of <hi>Christ</hi> of none effect. Reade alſo about this matter the ninth Chapter to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and when you have weighed it, ſee whether it can ſtand with the Lords Juſtice to call any of his ſervants to hear ſo in their bodies and ſpirits (as they do) his Juſtice and exact Judgment, untill he have wrought out of them his own ſatisfaction &amp; recompence in that nature. But if Satan ſhall teach them a point of Sophiſtry, and make them ſay they do not undergo this Wrath and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Satisfaction but for Sanctification, yet it will be a Lie and deluſion that way, for the Spirit of the Lord when it ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the hearts of his ſervants, doth not go about to tear their hearts out of their bodies, and their fleſh off their bones, in that nature. And although it be compared and many times called Fire in the Scripture, it is rather from the work wrought, than from the manner of its working; and therefore the Holy Spirit is compared unto Water, <hi>Iſai</hi> 55. <hi>&amp; John</hi> 4. And the Apoſtle ſaith concerning the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. that they were
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118718:17"/>waſhed from their former tranſgreſſions by the Spirit of the Lord, by which ſeemingly contrary expreſſions an impartial man may judg that the Spirit of the Lord worketh ſanctification in the ſoul, in a bleſſed, ſweet, moderate and peaceable manner.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as it is a Light, ſo it diſcovereth unto the ſoul the dangerouſneſs and uglineſs of ſin, and the unpleaſingneſs thereof unto the Lord.<note place="margin">The manner of the Spirit ſanctifying the heart.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, when it hath thus diſcovered it, it bringeth the ſoul to a diſliking thereof, it begins to take away the affections and the delights of the heart from it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in as much as the Spirit of the Lord is called a quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening Spirit, it doth raiſe up the ſoul to the contemplations of heavenly ways and duties, wherein the Lord would have his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to walk, and engageth the heart to love them, and ſo in an holy bleſſed alluring manner, ſtealeth the heart away to God, who in the manifeſtation of that Spirit of Light is made appear to the ſoul more lovely, excellent, rich, ſatisfactory, and the like, than, all thoſe former things were they riches or profane pleaſures wherein the ſoul delighted it ſelf before; herein I appeal to the witneſs of ſuch who have taſted of that Spirit; hence it is that the Lord is ſaid to allure his Church, and to ſpeak kindly unto her, and you ſhall finde how bleſſedly the Lord ſpeaketh unto a back-ſliding people (the worſt of all ſorts) upon their returnings unto him, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 14.4. I will heal their back ſlidings, I will love them freely, for mine anger is turned away from them. Me thinks if the Lord would have uſed ſuch fi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and fagot like burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings upon the hearts and conſciences of any people for to have ſanctified them withall, it ſhould have been upon ſuch a people as theſe are. But to end this which the Saints know by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and moſt others by report to be true; I ſhall turn over all that reade my Book unto that Parable of the polluted childe in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. from the beginning to <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. where you ſhall finde both the Lords purpoſe for acceptation of that polluted Babe, and his powerfull operations for its ſanctification in <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. and others.</p>
            <p>Moreover, if they ſhall urge <hi>Davids</hi> complaining, that his bones were broken, and his fleſh would ſcarce cleave unto them,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118718:18"/>and how he had no free part in his body, and the like; It is far from me to think, that this was under <hi>an apprehenſion of wrath,</hi> or that his ſoul did now bear the weight of Juſtice for its tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions or ſo; for <hi>David</hi> had long before ſaid and known that the Lord was wont to cover the ſins of his people, and not to impute them to their charge, and therefore he calls them bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 32.1, 2. and from this conifortable Doctrine of free forg veneſs and acceptation he concludeth his <hi>Pſalm</hi> with this, Be glad in the Lord, and rejoye O ye righteous, and ſhout for joy all ye that are upright in heart; for as he ſaith in the beginning of the next <hi>Pſalm,</hi> Praiſe is comely for the upright, ſo is a chearfull ſpirit upon this account. I rather take <hi>Davids</hi> complaining thus to be for want of his communion with God, as he ſeemeth to teach in that word, Thou hideſt thy face and I was ſore troubled. I am ſure the ſoul that hath had ſweet communion and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with and from the Lord, in the want of this will complain heavily, as you may finde in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 42. throughout; And by the Spouſe running ſo earneſtly after CHRIST when ſhe had loſt him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. in the beginning; And this made her cry out, ſhe was ſick of love for <hi>Christ.</hi> Was it not the want of the continued enjoyment of that extraordinary apprehenſion of love and glory in the preſence of God that made <hi>Paul</hi> complain, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. and ſuffer temptation, which he calleth a meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Satan? Shall any man think that he ſuffered this for his ſanctifying? Nay, will you now in the laſt place conſider how S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> doth reckon the fruit of the Spirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22, 23. The fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſs, goodneſs, faith, meekneſs, temperance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now compare their ſhakings, roarings out through extremity, cruel torturings of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and minde, which they call the fruits and operations of the ſpirit, with theſe fruits and operations which the Spirit of the Lord doth aſſume and take unto it ſelf, and then tell me which you will judg to be deluſion, for one muſt, becauſe they are ſo contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Demonstr.</hi> 4. From that great bondage and ſlavery which is laid upon them, they are captives by Satan at his will, and made to ſuffer more cruel burthens than the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were under <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> as you may ſee in theſe Particulars.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118718:18"/>
            <p> Firſt, whatſoever journey Satan ſhall ſuggeſt unto them, they muſt undertake it, if it be an hundred or two hundred miles, as I hear ſome have gone from ſome parts of the North unto <hi>London</hi> two hundred miles an end, and they muſt go with all expedition upon his command, and many times ſhall not have ſo much lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as to dreſs them firſt, (an hard Maſter, ſurely <hi>Christ</hi> was not wont to be ſo cruel unto his ſervants) and they ſay, they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to go, but whither to go, or to whom, or what to do, they know not, yet they muſt go like a blinde-folded man that knoweth not where his mark is; yet I ſuppoſe, Satan who is the greateſt Traveller himſelf that ever was, for he is ever compaſſing the Earth to and fro, and doth know all the parts thereof, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth the temperature of the peoples hearts in every corner of the Earth, when he ſendeth them his poor beguiled Vaſſals upon ſuch deſigns, he ſendeth them unto ſuch perſons be they many or few that are ready to be overcome and to yield unto ſuch tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as are offered unto them by theſe creatures, and ſo they ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom miſs of drawing ſome unſtable hearts into bondage with themſelves, under fair notions and pretences, unleſs it be where Satan himſelf is miſtaken concerning the faith and ſtedfaſtneſs of ſome ſoul, for what he does is at <hi>forte fortuna,</hi> hit or miſs, for they have come ſometimes unto me and to ſome others whom I know, pretending they were ſent of God in a ſpecial manner with a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to deliver, but I know they were deceived, and therefore by Satan; for the Lord is not wont to do things ignorantly, and to deceive his ſervants in that nature: and ſometimes they have not power to ſpeak, and therefore you may ſee how well the Lord ſent them; and if they be able to ſpeak, yet they are told their language is the Devils, and they come with a Lie in hypocriſie. Satan I ſuppoſe will not ſend very often where his Miniſters finde no better welcome.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the poor creatures are made to faſt from all manner of food ſometimes three days and three nights, and ſometimes as I have heard by them, when they have faſted thoſe three days and nights he commandeth them to faſt three more unto that, and when they do eat any thing it is with ſo much penuriouſneſs and ſcarcity that they are brought moſt feeble and wretched creatures by that means, contrary to the law and wiſdom of nature, which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118718:19"/>would teach a man to nouriſh and cheriſh his poor body if it were but with moderation; but as I ſaid once before, The Devil knows no mean, but is all upon extremes; either he maketh men meerly Gluttonous, as your Drunkards and Belly-gods, that can never hold till their bellies and chins do almoſt meet, or elſe he maketh other poor wretches ſterve themſelves, he doth ſo far de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them of natural affection, which you may well know to be his work, if you conſider of what kinde of people the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he maketh them go naked, as I have ſeen in ſome of their Books, and herein they glory by their expreſſions, and ſpeak how triumphantly they were made to come up naked into ſome Miniſters Pulpits in the North: and this I finde Satan doth act in them for theſe two Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the people (who are naturally <hi>novitatis avidi,</hi> greedy of news) might take theſe things to be as pety wonders or miracles; and indeed it cannot chuſe but make many ſimple people admire to ſee creatures faſt ſo long, and be able to go na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; hereby I do apprehend Satans deſign is to bring on theſe people to falſe works, as the Apoſtle calleth them, and as I do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſhew when I come directly upon that Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Satan doth labor by weakning and diſabling their poor bodies in this nature to bring them the ſooner to their diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if the Lord prevent not, that ſo he might exerciſe his will more fuily upon them: for certainly as the ſervants of <hi>Christ</hi> while they bear about them their earthly tabernacles, are not ſo capable either of glorifying God, or bearing the glory of God; ſo the Miniſters of <hi>Antichrist</hi> in this their being are not ſo fit to act or ſuffer what he would appoint them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they are made to deny their Callings, Profeſſions and honeſt Imployments many or moſt of them, and to neglect and diſregard their Families and new Relations, and to ſay it is the language of <hi>Antichrist</hi> that biddeth a man take care for his own houſhold and family, and ſome of them have ſaid to me, when I have been inquiring what our families ſhould do if all Callings and Labors ſhould be ſo neglected, that truly they muſt ſhift for themſelves, which I thought was very ſtrange teaching, for my heart was very tender of my near alliances in the fleſh,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118718:19"/>and they are a people for as many as I know of them that are wholly poſſeſſed with a principle of idleneſs, and going about from place to place, pretending that they are ſo moved of the Lord to go hither and thither, and if they are ſet about any honeſt work or deſign, I mean in civil affairs, if Satan do but ſuggeſt any thing to the contrary, they neglect it, and give it over preſently, if it be of never ſo great concernment, this I know by them, ſaying, They muſt leave all to obey the voice of CHRIST, and to follow him to whatſoever he commandeth them, and they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come altogether unprofitable to their generations, and fit for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to carry about the abominable deceits, ſuggeſtions and Lies of <hi>Antichrist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Rule which is my experience herein,<note place="margin">Rule 2. in Dem 4. is Experience.</note> and that (through mercy) is not much beſides the underſtanding of this deceit from them: onely in the buſineſs of Faſting my fancy was ſomewhat carried away; for I could have forborn Eating and Drinking, me thoughts for a great while, but through the perſwaſions of my Table-compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I would eat more than I had a deſire to, becauſe I would not give them offence; but I am perſwaded, had I been left to my own freedom, I ſhould have brought my ſelf unto a very low con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of body.</p>
            <p>But as for the giving over of laboring and following of worldly buſineſs, I could bear with them in that, me thoughts; for when I conſidered that moſt men are overcome and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited with the care and love of the things of this life, I thought the people of God ſhould be upon the extreme on the other hand.</p>
            <p>The third Rule is to conſider by what Scripture and Example Satan doth conceal this his deceit.<note place="margin">Rule 3. Demonſtr 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, for his acting of them to go and to run up and down an hundred or two hundred miles, ſomtimes more, ſometimes leſs, and to go they know not whither, nor to what end; he blindeth them with the Lords ſending the Prophets from place to place, as you reade of <hi>Jonahs</hi> going to <hi>Niniveh, Jon.</hi> 1. and the Prophet <hi>Ezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> being ſent to and fro between <hi>Judea</hi> and <hi>Chaldea;</hi> and then for their coming together and ſitting like a company of dumb crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for I know not how long, and ſometimes it may be they ſay
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118718:20"/>nothing at all when they are come together, and come to the place or perſon where they pretend they are ſent of God. And for this deceit you ſhall finde it coloured over with that inſtance of the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> who when he came to the captives at <hi>Tel<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abib</hi> that dwelt by the River of <hi>Kebar,</hi> was conſtrained to wait in great amazement for the ſpace of ſeven days before the Lord was pleaſed to manifeſt his minde concerning that people, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.15, 16. Now this coloureth over their dumbneſs and ſilence, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending they wait for the Viſion, Inſpiration or Revelation, as that Prophet did. And they have alſo a Gloſs put upon the words of CHRIST to his Diſciples, when he bade them Take no care what to ſpeak, for it ſhould be given them in the ſame hour what to ſay.</p>
            <p>Then for that geſture and principle of going naked, they have a colour from that inſtance of <hi>Saul</hi> ſtripping off his cloathes and propheſying naked, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.24. And they may finde the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle when he is ſpeaking of the perſecutions, ſay, that ſometimes he ſuffered hunger, and cold, and nakedneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, for that deceit of theirs in giving over all care and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and their honeſt imployment in the world, they are made to miſ-apprehend the teachings of CHRIST, in <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.37, 38. He that will not take up his Croſs and follow me is not worthy of me: here they think that CHRIST doth engage his people to leave off all care and diligence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And thoſe words of CHRIST in <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.31, 34. where he biddeth his Diſciples take no thought what they ſhould eat or drink, or wherewith they ſhould be cloathed, neither would he have them take thoughts for to morrow, for to morrow (ſaith he) ſhall take thoughts for it ſelf: and ſuch other like Scriptures as theſe which Satan is well acquainted withall. But ſuch who are kept under the power and teachings of the Spirit of God do know the minde of <hi>Christ</hi> about the outward things.</p>
            <p>The fourth Rule is the teaching of the Spirit of God in ſuch things as theſe are.<note place="margin">Rule 4. in Demonſtr. 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As to their going from place to place far remote, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to particular perſons, we know that the Lord was wont to make great uſe of his ſervants in this nature; <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Egypt</hi> to deliver the Embaſſie of God unto <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> but he
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118718:20"/>would not hearken; ſo ſay they, it may fall out many times that our meſſage will not be received. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was ſent to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptives by the River of <hi>Chebar,</hi> but the Lord had told him, they ſhould ſhew themſelves a rebellious people, and would not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: ſo it may be with them, they ſay. <hi>Christ</hi> himſelf ſpake with authority, and in ſuch a manner that moſt that heard him wondered, yet how doth he complain of the unbelief and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the people hearts? ſo they ſpeak many times as though it were with authority, and I believe it is with a great deal of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudency and boldneſs; for I reade in what an inſolent, proud and authentick manner the Devil ſpake unto the face of <hi>Christ, Mark</hi> 5.7. ſaying, I adjure thee by God that thou torment me not; and is it any marvel if he ſhall act his ſervants and miniſters to ſpeak with ſuch audaciouſneſs ſometimes unto the Diſciples of <hi>Christ,</hi> ſeeing they are not above their Maſter?</p>
            <p>The Lord alſo ſent <hi>Ananias</hi> to <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 9. <hi>Peter</hi> was likewiſe ſent to <hi>Cornelius</hi> by Viſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. <hi>Philip</hi> was ſent by ſpecial command unto the Eunuch as he was travelling. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> was ſent to <hi>David, Jonah</hi> to <hi>Nineveh, Paul</hi> himſelf was bound in ſpirit to go unto <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and from hence they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they have ground ſufficient for going to particular perſons by Viſion or Revelation as well as theſe whom God ſent: ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king themſelves to be either Prophets or Apoſtles. But let him that would know this deluſion mark theſe differences.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Lord ſending theſe laſt mentioned ſervants of his to theſe ſeveral and particular men, You finde the power of God ſo much manifeſted in them and by them, that the Word of the Lord was bleſſed and made ſuccesfull unto the hearts of thoſe unto whom it was brought. But theſe deluded creatures, although they come with as a fair pretence and gloſs as the other did (for <hi>Antichrist</hi> in this fitteth in the ſeat of God in a ſpecial manner) yet their word proveth but a Lie or an imagination of their own brain.</p>
            <p>Secondly, obſerve, that if they do prevail upon any poor ſouls by this high myſtery of deceit, they are either</p>
            <p n="1">1. Such as are meerly ignorant, uneſtabliſhed, and unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted both with the ways of <hi>Christ</hi> or <hi>Antichrist</hi> in this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:118718:21"/> 2. They are ſuch who are meer Notionaliſts, that have been full of brave words, but have had but little if any of the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full actings of Truth and Grace in their ſouls, not walking and maintaining cloſe communion together in any viſible, exemplary and juſtifiable way and order of the Goſpel. And therefore let it not be thought ſo ſtrange to ſee ſuch carried away, for they have been but like clouds without water, as <hi>Jude</hi> ſaith, and ſo might eaſily be blown about with every winde of doctrine: but bleſſed be the Lord, I do not hear or know any that have been well grown and experienced Chriſtians, walking and maintaining a cloſe and ſtrict communion and fellowſhip together according to thoſe exemplary ways of <hi>Christ</hi> and his Diſciples, that are thus overcome and betrayed by the ſubtil wiles of the Devil: and this I would have all the world to take ſpecial notice of, and ſo it may be a means of unvailing unto their underſtandings that cloſe and dangerous deceit under pretence of being ſent with a ſpecial word from the Lord unto ſuch a perſon, people or place.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let this be alſo well obſerved, theſe Dreamers ſay, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they pretend it is the Lord by ſome ſpecial Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Inſpiration, or Operation, (be it what it will, the Lord muſt be the Author thereof, if we will believe them) that ſendeth them hither or thither, that they know not whither to go, or to what perſon, till they come to the place or perſon, and when they are come whither they apprehend they were ſent, yet they ſay, that they know not what to do or ſpeak untill that be given them by Inſpiration alſo. Now let us return and examine the manner of the Lords ſending his ſervants and Prophets upon ſuch particular meſſages, and we ſhall finde it to be far otherwiſe; for the Lord was wont when he ſent them to tell them unto whom to go, and likewiſe what to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Moſes</hi> was ſent to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> he was taught at firſt by the Lord to whom to go and what to ſay.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Nathan</hi> was ſent to <hi>David</hi> he was told to whom to go and what to ſay, 2 <hi>Sa.</hi> 12. the beginning. When <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was to go to the River of <hi>Chebar,</hi> he was told to whom to go, onely at that time (I never read the like any where elſe to my preſent remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance) he was made to wait upon the Lord for the manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his pleaſure.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:118718:21"/>
            <p> When <hi>Jonah</hi> was ſent to <hi>Nineveh,</hi> he was told from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to whom to go, and what to ſay.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Ananias</hi> was ſent to <hi>Paul,</hi> he was told to whom to go, and what to ſay, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.10.11.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Peter</hi> was ſent to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> he was inſtructed by his Viſion what to ſay, and by three men that came to him, to whom to go, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Note well this difference and ſo judg.</p>
            <p>Secondly, concerning their going naked. I never knew the minde of the Lord ſo diſcovered by any of his ſervants either un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the old or new Covenant. And as for that of <hi>Sauls</hi> ſtripping off his cloaths and lying down naked among the Prophets, there is nothing in that place that doth prove it to be the will of the Lord, or that he was ſo acted and commanded of him; and let it not ſcruple any one that the Lord gave him a ſpirit of Propheſie at that time, for why might not the Lord make <hi>Saul</hi> propheſie, as well as make <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſs ſpeak, <hi>Numb.</hi> 23. ſeeing he was a more likely creature for ſuch a work?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, whereas they give over their Callings, Profeſſions, honeſt Imployments in the world, and give themſelves over to idleneſs, and pretend they muſt have nothing to do with the World, but muſt be ready at a beck to run hither and thither when the Lord ſhall ſend them, and the like: Such who reade the Scriptures know how the Spirit of God was wont to ſpeak and teach his ſervants about theſe things, that their moderation muſt be known unto all men, and that they ſhould uſe the World as though they uſed it not, and that it was more honorable to give than receive, and that he that would not work ſhould not eat, and that every man ſhould provide things honeſt before all men, and take care for their families and houſholds, which they call the Language of <hi>Antichrist;</hi> but Nature and Grace (for the one deſtroyeth not but rather perfecteth the other) do both teach the ſervants of CHRIST that this is true in the main, and how to uſe it in a mean: and do we not know how <hi>Paul</hi> was wont ſometimes to labor had night and day at his Calling, becauſe he would not be troubleſom or chargeable to a poor people? And did not the Diſciples of CHRIST follow their Callings when they had need or conveniency? And doth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118718:22"/>not <hi>Paul</hi> adviſe ſuch as ſhould be called to the knowledg of the Truth to reſt ſatisfied in that eſtate, condition or calling wherein they ſhould be called, if any were called being a ſervant that he ſhould not be diſſatisfied; if any were called being free, he ſhould rather deſire to continue ſo?</p>
            <p>I muſt intreat my Readers to note theſe Scriptures as they reade them, for in regard of the ſcarcity of my time and multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of buſineſs, I am conſtrained to neglect the quotation of them here, and ſo to paſs more briefly and ſcantingly over things than I would otherwiſe have done willingly, and glad I am to finde ſo much time as that my Pen might run with much ſpeed to what it doth ſinglely without any Copy.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now give the World but this one diſcovery more in this nature, and that ſhall be ſuch an one that (had I ſpake no more) might have given a ſufficient underſtanding of this moſt horrible and dangerous deceit under which theſe creatures lie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Demostr.</hi> 5. I do collect from that ſpirit of enmity, bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and prejudice which is conceived and brought forth in their hearts towards ſuch of the ſervants of <hi>Christ</hi> who walk moſt ſtrictly and orderly in their fellowſhips and communions toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and towards ſuch of them, eſpecially ſuch as are the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the Truth in the Churches of <hi>Christ,</hi> and that are moſt eminently gifted, and moſt inſtrumental in the hands of <hi>Christ</hi> for the advancement of his Kingdom. This I know to be too true by what I obſerved in my own experience of this nature when I was under thoſe Sataniſh-angelical-metamorphoſings; beſide that, I have heard them ſay ſeveral times, their hearts were more drawn out towards the creatures of the world, that they were more tenderly affected toward ſuch who were meetly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtical and profane creatures, than towards ſuch and ſuch So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, Fellowſhips, Profeſſions and Profeſſors, and the like. And this may be witneſſed by their railing, lying, clamorous, falſe accuſing Letters which they have writ againſt many preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, honeſt-hearted men that I know, and yet they pretend all this is done in love.</p>
            <p>Now will we try whether this inward core, ſecret prejudice, falſe ſurmiſe and heart-burning againſt the ſervants of <hi>Christ</hi> be the work of <hi>Christ</hi> or <hi>Antichrist.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:118718:22"/>
            <p> It will every way appear they are under an horrible deluſion in this very thing, when the matter is clearly examined, for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, if they cannot ſee the ſervants of <hi>Christ</hi> that walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the manifeſt Rules of the Goſpel to be the ſervants of <hi>Christ,</hi> but reckon them to be the ſervants of ſin, hypocrites, men in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> acted onely by that firſt created excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or light received, and the like, as they do commonly; why then they prove themſelves to be blinded and led forth by a lying and deceivable ſpirit of deluſion by <hi>Antichrist,</hi> like unto the men of the world, that do not know the Servants and Diſciples of <hi>Christ</hi> from his profeſſed Enemies, but ſpeak evil of the things and men they know not, and ſo there needs no further proof than their own open and profeſſed miſtake, ranking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the carnal and ſinfull men of the world, who are all under the power of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> as you ſhall finde in the words of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. In times paſt, ſaith he, meaning the time of irregeneration, Ye walked according to the courſe of this world, and according to the Prince of the power of the Air, the ſpirit that now worketh in the children of diſobedience; and moreover, ſaith he in <hi>v.</hi> 12. At that time (meaning this time laſt mentioned) ye were without <hi>Christ,</hi> aliens from the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſtrangers from the Covenant of Promiſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no hope, and without God in the world. O ye poor delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded creatures of the world alſo! your ſpirits and perſons I love and wiſh well unto, and therefore as my brethren in the firſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I deſire you all in the bowels and mercies of <hi>Christ,</hi> to weigh well and conſider this Scripture, for here is your condition exactly and truly characterized and held forth unto you; and when any of you ſhall finde it ſo, give neither the Lord nor your own ſouls any reſt untill you finde your ſelves in ſome meaſure waſhed and ſanctified by the Spirit of <hi>Christ</hi> from that uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable condition. But to return.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if theſe poor beguiled wretches of whom we are ſpeaking all along, ſhall judg them to be the ſervants of <hi>Christ,</hi> and reckon themſelves the ſervants of <hi>Christ</hi> alſo, why then they are brethren, and if brethren, and yet hate their brethren, they muſt needs be under deluſion, and the words of the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> will render them to be Liars and a deceived
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118718:23"/>people, to take the words of the Apoſtle before us.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>John</hi> 3.10. In this the Children of God are manifeſt, and the Children of the Devil; whoſoever doth not righteouſneſs [Look to that O ye unrighteous men!] is not born of God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he that loveth not his brother.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 14. We know that we are paſſed from Death to Life, becauſe we love the brethren; he that loveth not his brother abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 15. Whoſoever hateth his brother is a murderer, and ye know no murderer hath eternal life abiding in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 7. Beloved, let us love one another, for love is of God, and every one that loveth is born of God, and knoweth God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8. He that loveth not knoweth not God, for God is love.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12. No man hath ſeen God at any time, if we love one another God dwelleth in us, and his love is made perfect in us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 16. He that dwelleth in love, dwelleth in God and God in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Verſ.</hi> 20. If any man ſay he loveth God, and hateth his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he is a Lyar.</p>
            <p>This teſtimony of <hi>John</hi> proveth all manner of envy, hatred, bitterneſs, evil ſurmiſings, and the like, againſt the ſervants of <hi>Christ,</hi> to be none of the work of God, becauſe God is love, and acteth all in love, and as he doth act, and as he is, ſo are his ſervants in this preſent world, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p>But if they ſhall go about to perſwade further, and to ſay, that notwithſtanding they ſpeak ſharp and harſh language, yet it is all from a principle of love, This will not agree with that ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of divine love which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> mentioneth 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4, 5, 6, 7.</p>
            <p>Charity ſuffereth long, and is kinde, it envieth not, it vaunteth not it ſelf, it doth not behave it ſelf unſeemly, ſeeketh not her own, is not eaſily provoked, thinketh none evil, rejoyceth not in iniquity but rejoyceth in the Truth, beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things.</p>
            <p>Now let any judicious man compare the operations of that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118718:23"/>which they call divine love, and theſe operations which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth here mention, and ſee whether they are like to proceed from one author.</p>
            <p>If I had uſed onely this one Demonſtration it might have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freed to have proved them to be under a moſt deceitfull power of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> but while here are variety of diſcoveries with plain and eaſie Rules for manifeſtation thereof, I ſuppoſe he muſt be wilfully blind that will be lead away with theſe people and their pernicious Errors, when he ſhall have well weighed and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red one thing with another. I do not for the preſent apprehend any thing more material to have been illuſtrated in this nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide what I have done: I will therefore proceed to what I finde next to be conſidered in the Apoſtles diſcoverings of them, which is, that as Satan transforms himſelf into an Angel of Light, ſo it will be no great thing to ſee his miniſters transformed as miniſters of righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>The ſecond remarkable Truth from the Text is thus:</p>
            <p>That ſuch as are be guiled by Satans angelical transformings of himſelf in the manner as hath been ſhewed, are likewiſe transformed themſelves as though they were Miniſters of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</p>
            <p>For if it were not ſo, they would preſently diſcover it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> if ſuch a wonderfull and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry power ſhould appear exerciſing and terrifying both their bodies and mindes, and yet they themſelves carried forth as miniſters of unrighteouſneſs they would apprehend it not to be of God, and all other people for the moſt part would know it ſo likewiſe; whereas they now ſtand amazed not knowing what to think of it; for every one can ſee and ſay, that is not quite blinde, that all open, profane, wicked, lewd, unconſcionable and unrighteous men, are deluded of the Devil, and by him lead into thoſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ways of ſin and uncleanneſs, for God never leadeth men into ſuch courſes. Note this all you that go aſtray from the ways of holineſs, and ſin againſt your own Light; and being ſo in the ways of unrighteouſneſs, Satan findeth himſelf to be open and unmasked, he transforms his miniſters as well as himſelf, and ſo maketh them act as though they were Miniſters of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and that they were indeed moved thereunto of the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:118718:24"/>
            <p> And this is the reaſon why this prodigious Comet doth through theſe its ſcintillations and ſparklings beget ſuch a dreadfulneſs in the hearts of the beholders, and to ſpeak out, I am afraid it doth prognoſticate a ſad deſtiny unto many people, as I ſhall ſhew to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the end of my Book, onely ſuch who walk in the ſtatutes and ordinances of CHRIST ſhall be kept by him as Lambs in his boſom, but let all other wandring ſtars and empty clouds, ſuch who are mighty in words and expreſſions, little or nothing in a ſound, experimental and lively knowledg of CHRIST, look to themſelves, and if this cautionary word make any of them wiſe, let them glorifie God on that behalf,</p>
            <p>Did you ever know a people acted through a more glorious ſhew or appearance of righteouſneſs than they are?</p>
            <p>Their denying and throwing off the world, and all the cares and pains thereof for <hi>Christs</hi> ſake, as they ſay, and their forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king father, mother, wife and children, What a fair colour hath this?</p>
            <p>Their enduring ſo much affliction, oppoſition, perſecution and diſgrace from men, Is not this like the Croſs of <hi>Christ?</hi> and like the ſuſterings of <hi>Christ</hi> and his Apoſtles? Their running and travelling ſo many miles from place to place, and ſpeaking ſo boldly unto great men, crying out againſt their abominations, Doth not this blace abroad mightily in the eys of the world? Their writing ſo many Letters, and dealing ſo plainly with men, carrieth a fair ſhew of holineſs.</p>
            <p>And there are hardly a people to be found that cry out more againſt <hi>Antichrist</hi> and all appearances of ſin and unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs than they do; and this I believe doth ſtumble many ignorant hearts.</p>
            <p>But let ſuch conſider, that if a man call himſelf Knave, or ſpeak evil againſt himſelf, it is no ſtander, neither doth he take it amiſs: ſo for Satan to cry out againſt himſelf is no offence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and this is but a ſmall game for him to play in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome other he doth, and will yet uſe more and more if the Lord permit him. How can he be rightly ſaid to transform him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into an Angel of Light, if he do not ſeemingly act the part of God, and make his miniſters act as the Miniſters of Righte. ouſneſs?</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:118718:24"/>
            <p> Theſe people, if you obſerve them well, are ſuch a people that would ſeem to be very blameleſs in their whoſe carriage, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will not ſpeak words that be evil, they will ceaſe from ſpeaking thoſe that are good.</p>
            <p>And becauſe they will not uſe a labour, pains or care that ſhall be evil, they will neglect that which is honeſt, good, and juſt: theſe in a vain ſhew of will worſhip in neglecting their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.23. thus ſeem to go beyond the very Servants and Miniſters of CHRIST indeed.</p>
            <p>The whole bulk of their hitherunto actings as far as I know or have heard, do declare them to be carried forth as Miniſters of Righteouſneſs, and ſo muſt all that are beguiled of Satan in this nature be deceitfully transformed like himſelf, otherwiſe as I have ſaid, they would eaſily finde out the myſtery of this deceit themſelves, and it would quickly appear to others alſo; and this you ſee is agreeable to the diſcovery which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth through the ſpirit of diſcerning, in order to this ſecret delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>I know not any thing of concernment that I ſhould amplifie upon this Truth; moreover the importunities of ſome things do neceſſitate me to haſten towards a period with all poſſible expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and therefore I ſhall proceed to the next obſervation in my Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctrine</hi> 3. That when Satan hath transformed himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Angel of Light, and hath transformed his miniſters as Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Righteouſneſs, he will not let them reſt there (reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that to be too low an honor for ſuch faithfull friends) but will advance them even to become falſe Apoſtles, being tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into the Apoſtles of CHRIST, and then they ſhall be qualified fit for their attainments, and made able to do deceitfull works.</p>
            <p>Here let all perſons note by the way how methodical <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ</hi> is in his School; firſt he will make them his miniſters, and afterwards they ſhall be made like the Apoſtles of <hi>Christ;</hi> here is his ſubtilty in his gradations, he hath not judged it ſafe for him to begin too high for fear of being diſcovered, but doth walk ſoftly, and ſo for himſelf more ſafely, like as though he had learned that Philoſophical Maxime, <hi>Violentus motus nunquam diuturnus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:118718:25"/>
            <p> This maſter-piece of work is yet behinde, I mean his making theſe creatures mechanical able to do deceitfull works with their hands, as the Apoſtles did by laying their hands upon the ſick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But what will the world think when they ſhall be raiſed a degree higher than this yet, and appear as falſe <hi>Christs?</hi> for we all know that CHRIST himſelf did propheſie there ſhould be falſe <hi>Christs, Matth.</hi> 24.23, 24. and falſe Prophets, and ſhould ſhew great ſigns and wonders, and ſhould deceive, nay, if it were poſſible the very elect ſervants of <hi>Christ</hi> ſhould be deceived by them.</p>
            <p>Let all people well conſider this Propheſie of <hi>Christ,</hi> together with that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.9. Here is mention made of a way of Satans working with all power, and ſigns, and lying wonder.</p>
            <p>There is a principle in moſt part of the ignorant people of the world that leads them after news, and this hath been of old in the days of <hi>Christ</hi> himſelf, for the unbelieving creatures were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways gazing after ſigns and wonders, and ſo they are now, but by ſuch time I ſhall write ſomething more of this, and you ſhall well conſider what I have writ, I ſuppoſe there will be but little encouragement to look after ſigns and wonders.</p>
            <p>Some men think that Satan cannot do miracles and wonders; indeed I do now remember I have ſometimes read this difference in ſome of the later Syſtems of Divinity, that <hi>Quanquam mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula non poſſit, tamen mira potest.</hi> Let men call his actings in this nature what they will, they will be big enough and ſtrange enough to deceive many unſtable ſouls withall: and if you do but remember the Hiſtory of <hi>Moſes</hi> miracles wrought in <hi>Egypt</hi> before <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> you may likewiſe finde how the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians could do the like things with <hi>Moſes,</hi> as long as the Lord would ſuffer. Spare me the labor, and reade the Hiſtory your ſelves, <hi>Exod.</hi> 7, <hi>&amp;</hi> 8. <hi>chap.</hi> to <hi>v.</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>And what do men uſe to call thoſe horrid and dreadfull acts that are brought to paſs ſometimes in ſtorms and tempeſts, as the ſplinting and throwing down of trees, removing of great ſtones, and the like, which are commonly known in the experience of Countreys and Nations?</p>
            <p>Are theſe actings of <hi>Antichrist</hi> ſo lovely that you deſire ſigns
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118718:25"/>and wonders, if you knew what Satan can do by creatures in whom he acts as he doth in them, you would rather rather deſire to be hid from them: you may reade that ſad exigent that fell out by the power of the Devil in a poor creature, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.16. The man in whom the evil ſpirit was leapt on them, and overcame them, and prevalled againſt them; ſo that they fled out of the houſe naked and wounded, and it was well they could eſcape ſo.</p>
            <p>If ſuch things as theſe ſhould be ſhewed upon ſome of thoſe ignorant people that are hearkning after this ſo much, it would make them weary hereof quickly.</p>
            <p>As for my part, I do expect to ſee theſe kinde of creatures brought ſo far by that <hi>Antichristian</hi> power under which they are ſo firmly kept, as that they ſhall Apoſtle-like or <hi>Christ</hi>-like be able to do great things to the amazement of ſuch as ſhall be ingorant of theſe devices, and they themſelves to my knowledg do live in expectation of ſuch a power, and make their boaſt thereof,<note place="margin">The ſtory of a wonder.</note> and ſome of them have told me a ſtory which I will here inſert, to the end the world may be prepared in ſome meaſure with faith and knowledg, that they may not be too much carried away with theſe things when they are more publick: and I for my own part am apt to think it might be true. It is as followeth.</p>
            <p>They told me there was a man in the North, I took it then by conjecture to be either <hi>Fox</hi> or <hi>Nailer,</hi> who was commanded (as he ſaid) of the Lord to faſt a great while, (if my memory fail me not) they told me at the firſt it was ſeven days and ſeven nights, and having ſo done he was commanded to faſt ſo many more next enſuing, but if through ſome ſuſpition I have of my memory in this particular of time, I ſhall not be poſitive, yet I do well remember they have told me of three days and three nights, and ſo many more preſently after that ſeveral of them have been commanded to faſt: but here is the little-great wonder, this man having faſted, whether twice ſeven days and nights or twice three, it matters not much to me, but having ſo faſted as he was commanded by his Enemy under pretence of a friend, he was commanded to go into ſuch a Well in a certain place that he knew, and ſo he did, and he was appointed to drink of that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118718:26"/>which he did, having taken ſomething with him for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and when he drank he apprehended it to be pure and perfect good Wine, and ſo he drank no more, but on the morrow he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned unto the ſaid Well, to ſee whether it were ſo continued or not, and then he found it meer Water as at other times.</p>
            <p>Here was a remarkable thing, which I believe to be true, for I am perſwaded they dare not tell a Lie, knowing it to be ſo; and if this were true, then I ſhall be bold to affirm there was a falſe <hi>Christ</hi> appeared, for we know that <hi>Christ</hi> converted Water into Wine at a Marriage in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> and becauſe <hi>Christ</hi> did ſo, therefore Satan he cometh as it were the ſame <hi>Christ,</hi> doing the ſame thing: but let not this be thought very ſtrange by any one that reades my lines, that Satan ſhould be able to do this, for it was a far eaſier matter for him to turn one Cup of Water into Wine to deceive this poor ſilly man, than it was for him to turn all the Rivers, ſtreams and Ponds that were in <hi>Egypt</hi> into bloud, <hi>Exod.</hi> 7.19, 22. Or haply he might not really turn this Water into Wine, and yet he might really deceive the man, in deluding his taſte; for you muſt know that Satan can eaſily delude a mans ſenſes, as I have ſeen by theſe Jugglings and Popper-plays, and the like.</p>
            <p>I have heard them tell me ſome other fine things of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which I ſhall forbear to cite in regard they are no news to me, becauſe I do apprehend that they muſt become falſe Apoſtles and falſe <hi>Christs</hi> to do great ſigns and wonders: yet this I do obſerve by the way, that Satan is ſo politick, that he will not do as yet any terrible acts by them, whereby he might fear or amaze the people, as he did by that man in <hi>Acts</hi> 19. for then he might loſe them before he had gained them; but he will rather chuſe to do things that may be delightfull and pleaſing unto the people, ſuch as healing ſome infirmities, and turning of Water into Wine, and the like; and truly this is ſuch a deceivable way, that if he ſhould uſe it much, it would be enough to make all the Drunkards and Sack-belly-gods in <hi>England</hi> to become <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, Comes hilaris quaſi vehiculum viatori,</hi> if it were but for that they might not empty their Purſes to fill their bellies.</p>
            <p>I ſhould gladly hear of the charge of that Principle there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that maketh ſo many ignorant people look after lying ſigns
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118718:26"/>and wonders, and to ſee them inquire after faith, and knowledg, and the grace of our Lord JESUS CHRIST, that ſo they might be able to ſtand in ſuch evil times as theſe are, while Satan is playing his laſt game; and let all the world aſſure themſelves, that we are now living in thoſe laſt times that the ſervants of <hi>Christ</hi> hinted in ſo many places; and indeed the moſt ignorant and ſcandalous men of our Nation called by the people like themſelves Miniſters and Preachers, have of late years been tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their people over and over this thing, but here was their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, not in the time but in the perſons and things, for they have reckoned and railed at the Churches and ſervants of <hi>Christ</hi> who did moſt endeavour to demean themſelves unto an exemplary and viſible order of the Goſpel, to be thoſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks and deluders of deluded people that are mentioned in the Scripture, but conſidering their ignorance and blindneſs unto the things, ways, adminiſtrations, and ſervants of <hi>Christ,</hi> it was well they could come ſo near as to point at the time ſo rightly, and I will forbear with them in this. Yet let not the Readers of my Book think that I take their teſtimony for my own confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, or ſhall offer it unto any other, but if you will forbear me in this place, you ſhall have my own grounds and reaſons with the Scripture to prove this thing hereafter in my firſt queſtion, onely I ſhall be bold before I go any further to tell all carnal and natural men in the world, be they Preachers or People, that they muſt be beholding to thoſe People whom they have ignorantly called Hereticks and Deluders. I mean the ſervants of <hi>Christ,</hi> not in form onely but in power, evidence and demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Spirit, to encounter with this ſpirituall myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity that reigneth in ſuch an high nature in the poor undone peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. There is nothing in any carnal man in the world that can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able him for this work, if they had all <hi>Apollo's</hi> wiſdom, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerva's</hi> learning, or <hi>Sampſons</hi> ſtrength, it would not help them, unleſs it were <hi>vi &amp; armis,</hi> by an arm of fleſh, and that would be next unto nothing.</p>
            <p>Peradventure this little labor of mine may make many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands able to refuſe their Errors and Deluſions, but it will not make any one able to reſiſt and encounter with it, <hi>Delinquere ſed non evincere,</hi> becauſe it can be done no way but through a greater
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118718:27"/>power, and ſtrength, and light than is in <hi>Antichrist:</hi> and he that ſhall obſerve me in this one thing ſhall ſee the reaſon hereof; becauſe Satan is by his creation an Angel of Light, ſuch as the reſt of them were; and we know that God made all things pure and good, he made no Devil nor wicked man, he made <hi>Adam</hi> an innocent righteous man, he made the Angels innocent and righteous, and far more excellent creatures than <hi>Adam</hi> was: now if you compare the greateſt excellency or glory in <hi>Adam</hi> while he was unchanged, with that light and glory of the bleſted Angels into which Satan hath now transformed himſelf again, you ſhall finde as much difference as you can judg between the light of a little ſtar and the great Sun; how much more then when you finde but the relicks, reverſions, and ſome ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders of <hi>Adams</hi> firſt excellency in any man that now liveth in that apoſtatized condition? Therefore I would ſain know how any man living in ſuch a low carnal ſtate of apoſtaſie ſhould be able to deal or to encounter with ſuch an angelical and mighty appearance of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> as is now manifeſt; Will not it be now a Truth unto your underſtandings, that there muſt be a greater light, power, glory and excellency thin his, be found out to match and overcome him, even that light, power, glory and excellency of the eternal being, brought forth in the hearts of the ſincere and faithfull ſervants of <hi>Christ?</hi> You know that <hi>Christ</hi> ſaith, If a ſtrong man keep the houſe then all things are ſafe untill a ſtronger than he cometh, but then <hi>Minima cedant maximis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What would a wicked, drunken, profane, ungodly man ſay for himſelf? if one of theſe creatures in whom there is ſuch a mighty power of <hi>Antichrist</hi> ſhould come unto him with ſo much audacity and boldneſs of ſpeech as the Devil came to the face of <hi>Chriſt, Mark</hi> 5.7. ſaying, I adjure thee by God that thou torment me not, and tell him plainly and with all authority, Thou art a damned wretch, there ſhall no ſuch as thou art enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, thou art ſuch and ſuch a creature, and all ſuch are fit for nothing but to undergo the eternal wrath of God, and the like: What would ſuch a miſerable creature be able to ſay for himſelf, he is conſcientious to himſelf that he is told truth? Where is the power now to reſiſt this mighty ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parances
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:118718:27"/>rance, and to filence this accuſer of the brethren? you will be leſt like <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> one knee ſmiting againſt another.</p>
            <p>Moreover, what if one of theſe creatures ſhould be ſent with much power and boldneſs unto a profane, ſcandalous Preacher, and made to tell him, He is a blinde Leader of a blinde People, and a man that crieth Lord, Lord, and that ſpeaketh of a <hi>Chriſt</hi> without, but knoweth not, neither hath he received any of the power, grace or Spirit of that <hi>Chriſt</hi> within? he ſpeaketh he knows not what, he telleth his people hey ſhould not be envetous, proud or ſinfull, and yet he him ſelf the Ring-leader of theſe baſe things; he is told further, he is onely an hireling, preacheth for Tyths and ſtipends, and if it were not for this he would not preach at all, and that he knows not what to ſay till he hath ſtollen it from other mens lines, he hath no experience of truth in his own ſoul, and lays this hard upon his conſcience, which will joyn with this his adverſary, and tell him all this is true, and by that time he hath charged him home with truth to his own knowledg, What a trembling, dumb and miſerable condition will this poor man be in, ſtanding like one ready for his diſſolution, notable to reply any wiſe word, like unto a pale-faced image that the ſtander by muſt cry, <hi>Opertet aliquid intus,</hi> and yet may be the man a good Scholar of great natural parts, a blazing ſtar in his countrey; but what is this ſtar-light worth when the Sun ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth? all his light is become darkneſs now by reaſon of that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical light which appeared in one of the miniſters of Satan be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a falſe Apoſtle or a falſe <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This me thinks ſhould be wonder big enough for ſuch who will not believe except they ſee wonders; but what will you ſay if you ſhould ſee Satan ſtirring up one of his foreſaid miniſters to fall upon any ſuch creature that is ſo naked and unarmed from all power of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his powerfull Spirit, and to tear him, hurt him, wound him, and peradventure take away his life alſo? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member ſtill that inſtance <hi>Acts</hi> 19.16. then it would make your hearts ake with wonders, and when by ſuch time you ſhall be told your own in this nature, you carnal and ignorant crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the world, you will believe it is not well with you, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding you had been told the ſame things ſeveral times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the ſervants of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by their preachings, writings and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:118718:28"/>diſcourſes in much love and tenderneſs: and moreover, when you ſhall ſee your ſelves not able to defend your ſelves againſt them, and yet ſhall ſee thoſe people you ſo much vilified, and reckoned the Hereteticks and Deluders, upon whom the Scripture was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, able to ſilence them, to defie them, to prove them through the power of Truth to be Deceivers, and falſe <hi>Chriſts,</hi> and falſe Apoſtles, and in the end to make the Devil flee from them as <hi>James</hi> ſaith, by their ſtrong reſiſtings of him with that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or compleat armour of God, ſpoken of <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.11. Reade on this Scripture you feeble creatures of the world and you ſhall finde that for want of this ſpiritual armour of proof it is that you are not able to deal with that mighty appearance and power in them: and on the other ſide by reaſon of the inveſting of the ſoul with this armour it is that the ſervants of <hi>Chriſt</hi> are able thus to foil them: and the more holy, heavenly, humble, ſeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denying, any of the ſervants of <hi>Christ</hi> are,<note place="margin">A Caution for Saints.</note> the more powerfully they will be able to withſtand all theſe fiery durts of the Devil. Note this all you holy ones of the Lord, and take heed that Satan finde no hole of covetouſneſs, pride, vain-glory, or the like, in any of your coats, for I will aſſure you if he do, you will have an hard match of him, as I know by experience in others.</p>
            <p>The breaking forth of things in this nature will bring honor to God and his ſervants before all the world, and convince them of the Truth, and make them ſee and know the people of God from others; and that there are none able to withſtand ſuch aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the Devil as theſe are either upon themſelves or others, but onely ſuch who have received power from <hi>Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I had here thoughts to have gone unto the laſt thing in the Text, but fearing leſt there ſhould be any ſcruple in the hearts of ſome ignorant people about their prevailing ſo much, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing their number in ſo many places of this Land, I will take away if I can the ground of this firſt.</p>
            <p>There hath been enough in my thoughts ſpoken to this already upon this laſt Doctrine of doing falſe works, for here I have ſhewed that they muſt act as Miniſters of Righteouſneſs, and thence they muſt come to act as falſe Apoſtles, nay as falſe <hi>Christs,</hi> and if they ſhall be brought to this, as <hi>Christ</hi> and his
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:118718:28"/>Apoſtles did true ſigns and wonders, ſo theſe muſt do lying ſigns and wonders, even ſuch things as <hi>Christ</hi> and his Apoſtles did, and if thoſe things wrought by <hi>Christ</hi> and the Apoſtles did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince and draw in many into their ways, why ſhall not the ſame things done now under the ſame ſhew and pretences draw in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as well into the ways of thoſe that do them?</p>
            <p>And beſide you ſhall reade in <hi>Acts</hi> 5.36. that there was one <hi>Theudas</hi> that roſe up among the people, boaſting himſelf to be ſome-body, (it is like far ſhort of theſe <hi>Quakers</hi>) to whom a number of men about four hundred joyned themſelves, who was ſlain, and as many as obeyed him were ſcattered and brought to nought. After him roſe up one <hi>Judas</hi> of <hi>Galile,</hi> in the days of the Taxing, and drew much people after him, he alſo periſhed, and as many as obeyed him were ſcattered.</p>
            <p>I hope in the conſideration of this there will remain no jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie about their increaſings, and if it ſhall ſtumble any one to ſee a few drawn in by them while they act but as Miniſters of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, hardly come up to that perfection of deceit to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtles or falſe <hi>Christs,</hi> then when they are come to this it may be a ſtumbling unto many, and they may draw whole multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of unſtable wretches for ought I know into their damnable ways.</p>
            <p>But you have a fair warning, therefore take heed.</p>
            <p>I am now come to the laſt thing in the Text, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whoſe end ſhall be according to their works.</p>
            <p>The very thoughts of this already do begin to ſadden my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; but according to my former method I will proceed.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine from the whole is thus.</p>
            <p>Such as Satan ſhall beguile by transforming himſelf into an Angel of Light unto them, untill they transform themſelves as Miniſters of Righteouſneſs, and then as falſe Apoſtles, ſhall come to an end ſuitable to their works: now let us examine their works, and then we ſhall know their end.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Their works are deceitfull, ſo their end will be; for whereas they themſelves have ſometimes thought, whatſoever they do now I know not, and others likewiſe concerning them, that they might have ended this their earthly being with a great
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118718:29"/>deal of comfort, peace and joy to themſelves and others, I am afraid they and others will be deceivers.</item>
               <item>2. Their works are railing and diſowning the power and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth; ſo I am afraid their end will be, a railing and ſpeaking againſt the pure and holy being of God.</item>
               <item>3. Their works are cruel torturings and perplexities both of body and minde; ſo it is to be doubted their conſciences will be in their diſſolution.</item>
            </list>
            <p>However, if any of them ſhall eſcape this, that the word of the Apoſtle may be true, and receive no prejudice by any private interpretation: their end at the beſt muſt be according to their works, for as their works are odious and ſhamefull unto all that know of what nature they are, becauſe they are brought forth through the power of <hi>Antichrist;</hi> ſo their end muſt be, if they are brought from under that power; for it will be a great deal of ſhame and trouble to them to ſee how they are beguiled by their Enemy, as it is unto my ſelf, when I conſider thereof, although there was no more in me but an approbation thereof, and a deſire after it, and the like, the power thereof was through the Lords goodneſs to my ſoul kept from me.</p>
            <p>Yet my former thoughts and expreſſions upon their end have a ſtrong confirmation from that place of <hi>Paul, Heb.</hi> 6.4, 5, 6. It is impoſſible for thoſe who who were firſt enlightned and have taſted of the heavenly gift, and were made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, and have taſted the good Word of God and the powers of the world to come, if they ſhall fall away, to renew them again unto repentance, ſeeing they crucifie to themſelves the Son of God afreſh, and put him to open ſhame.</p>
            <p>Now theſe people as far as I am or ever was able to diſcern them, were endued and that in a large meaſure with thoſe things the Apoſtle mentioneth; I mean many of them that I know whom I took in my former intimacy and communion with them to have received much of the power of Truth through <hi>Christ,</hi> and to have much communion with God and large experiments of his love, but as for many others of them they were never judged by me or the reſt to be any more than a willing people to inquire after the ways of the Lord, and as for ſuch this Scripture doth not touch him.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:118718:29"/>
            <p> But yet let us examine this Scripture a little farther, for I know it is a very myſterious one, and hath much puzled the thoughts of many good men, and in my apprehenſion there are two wrong judgments given upon it by moſt men.</p>
            <p>The one is, they generally take this Scripture to ſpeak forth nothing but eternal death and damnation to all ſuch who ſhall ſin and fail, as the Apoſtle doth there ſpeak, whereas the Apoſtle ſaith not any ſuch thing, but onely it is impoſſible to renew them unto repentance; and although it be true of men in general, without repentance there can be no ſalvation, yet <hi>Paul</hi> doth not here ſpeak of men that never had received CHRIST, but of men that had fallen away from and loſt what they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and therefore I hold good, in the ſpeaking upon this Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, to look diſtinctly upon the two conditions of inegeneration and apoſtacy.</p>
            <p>A ſecond wrong judgment given upon this Scripture as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive is, that this ſin here ſpoken is the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, which I do not ſo apprehend, and me thinks it will appear not to be ſo, from the laſt words in that place, for the utmoſt the Apoſtle reckons it unto, is, but the crucifying the Son of God afreſh, that is, the crucifying of a <hi>Chriſt</hi> without, or as he is in the heart of another, not his own that doth it; and we know that <hi>Christ</hi> himſelf ſaith, All manner of blaſphemy and ſin againſt the Son of man ſhall be forgiven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.31, 32. Here CHRIST himſelf doth not make any ſin againſt himſelf, that is, as he is not living and dwelling in the ſoul, to make a man without all conditions utterly uncapable of ſalvation for ever, for then all the world were uncapable of life, becauſe they ſin againſt that CHRIST which liveth and dwelleth in the hearts of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: But he maketh onely the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, that is, as I apprehend,<note place="margin">Diſcovery of the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, a wilful ſinning againſt the preſent operation and power of <hi>Chriſt</hi> or his Spirit.</note> againſt a living <hi>Chriſt</hi> within, not a <hi>Chriſt</hi> without, to render a man beyond and without all conditions whatſoever utterly uncapable of ſalvation, and this is the ſin which the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſaith is unto death, and therefore ought not to be prayed for, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.16. So that I cannot finde that the Apoſtle doth in theſe words point out any
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:118718:30"/>thing but ſuch a deſperate and dangerous Kinde of apoſtacy, as that he who ſhall be ſo qualified as there he ſpeaketh, and yet fall away, cannot poſſibly be brought to repentance, or out of that condition of apoſtacy while he continueth this being; and under this kinde of apoſtacy I finde many of theſe poor deluded creatures; as for thoſe that never received the grace of God in power and truth, they cannot be ſaid to fall from that they never had, and ſo their condition is not the ſame; but for the reſt of them I am afraid they will never be brought from under that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion while they live in their earthly tabernacles, for I ſee the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Spirit of CHRIST is wholly with drawn from them, and Satan he hath afterwards ſtollen away out of their hearts all thoſe bleſſed operations of his preſence, as faith, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, ſobriety, and enjoyments, and the like, and hath given them ſome droſs or counterfeit ſtuff in the ſtead thereof, ſuch as they take to be better and more pure metall than what they had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, and therefore they ſeem very much to rejoyce that they loſt it. O the moſt unparalleld apoſtacy and deluſion that ever was yet manifeſt!</p>
            <p>But if any one ſhall ask what I do judg to be the reaſon why the Lord CHRIST did with draw his preſence from theſe people, and ſo conſequently ſuffer Satan to rob them of their heavenly treaſure in this kinde? I ſhall by way of anſwer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto give one Reaſon, whereof I am confidently convinced, and another whereof I am but in part.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I am really perſwaded, was their negligence in uſing thoſe eminent gifts of ſpeaking praying, reaſoning, diſcourſing, build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up one another, and the like, wherewith they were endued, and that ſo largely, that I could not finde in my apprehenſions ſuch excellent attainments amongſt other people generally, which was the reaſon of engaging my affections ſo much to them above others; and as they grew negligent in uſing thoſe gifts, ſo from time to time they neglected keeping communion together, and became a ſcattered people, every one giving himſelf over to a ſelfiſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired condition, becauſe they were ſo full of knowledg that they found not one able to inſtruct another, or to be a means of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing any farther underſtanding, and thus by little and little the bond only being broken, which I reckon to be a cloſe and ſtrict
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:118718:30"/>communion of Saints under every atainment or diſcovery, therein watching over one another, and praying for and with one another, Satan carrieth away their hearts into a very meer confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, loſs and nothingneſs, and having brought them to that paſs he preſenteth them with ſomething under moſt fair and glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, whereunto he gaineth their affections, even as far as unto willing obedience, and ſo acteth them therein according as you have heard all along,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 2. Whereof I am but in part convinced, is, that perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture the Lord would have his people walk in ſome one way, adminiſtration or form (call it what you will) whereby they might be brought unto a perfect unity in heart, judgment and obedience, making but one eccho or voice both in their prayers and praiſes, that ſo all that indignity and diſgrace which is caſt upon the ſervants of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that in a great meaſure, juſtly might be taken away, for as yet the world ſay, that we cannot be the Church of <hi>Christ,</hi> becauſe we are ſo divided both in our judgments and practices, and me thinks I do apprehend the Lord as going about to take away all occaſion of ſtumbling of that nature from before the eys of the world, and to render his Church and people ſo like his people, that the enimies of <hi>Christ</hi> may ſee and ſay they are ſo indeed and in truth.</p>
            <p>And not onely for want of this is there a prejudice, ſuſpition and wrong judgment begot in the hearts of ſuch who are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, but alſo the hearts of the Lords own ſervants become very dead, cold and unprofitable to others, and uncomfortable to themſelves, and their gifts and graces for want of holy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual exerciſes do exceedingly fade away. I do not ſpeak this by report, but I have too much experience of this nature my ſelf, and ſo much it is, that I hope I ſhall not give over untill I finde through an holy and humble waiting and diligent inquiry ſome way or means of having my former enjoyments, refreſhings and bleſſed communion with the Lord and his CHRIST reſtored unto me again, for in the loſs of the former means and way of God wherein he was pleaſed moſt of all to afford me the comfort which was in a ſtrict and diligent maintaining communion of Saints, I am very ſenſible I loſt my comforts, and therefore I hope when I ſhall be brought into the ſame way again I may finde my
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:118718:31"/>former mercies, and much mercy and peace in <hi>Christ Jeſus</hi> be unto all ſuch who ſhall be ſolicitous at their Fathers Throne for the teachings of his Spirit in ſuch caſea of difficulty as this is, to deliver any of his poor ſervants out of theſe ſtraits.</p>
            <p>I had once thoughts in this place for the confirmation of my apprehenſions and expoſition upon <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. to have preſenced a rehearſal of a ſad ſelf-murther judgment which in theſe parts did lately befall one ſuch creature carried away with theſe deluders and their deluſions, who was for many years in my judgment, and ſo I think in moſt of the Lords people, a Pillar of Truth in the Church of <hi>Christ,</hi> and like a Mother in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but finding it to be an occaſion of glorying or rejoycing among the wicked in all theſe parts, I ſhall forbear to give any more of them this cauſe of bringing down their own judgments upon their own heads, hoping that this brief hint may ſuffice to teach all the children of God to ake heed.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Of living in a condition of idleneſs without any juſt or warrantable <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mployment.</item>
               <item>2. In growing cold in the ways and adminiſtrations of God, wherein their ſouls had been richly fed by him.</item>
               <item>3. Of neglecting, praying, watchfulneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Such things as theſe were the apparent and fore going cauſes of this ſore Judgment.</p>
            <p>And this inſtance maketh me afraid that but few ſuch once eminent of them will ever be brought to repentance, but have their end according to their works.</p>
            <p>I ſhall here leave off ſpeaking any further concerning this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion and the doctrines thereof, and would have fimſhed with this, were it not that there are two Queſtions of ſome concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that I conceive might be urged in order to theſe things and perſons whereof I have ſpoken.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Question</hi> 1. Why doth <hi>Antichrist</hi> act in this nature, and with ſo much fierceneſs, beyond what he hath been wont to do?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Firſt, becauſe he was neceſſitated hereunto, for theſe creatures would not be taken with Hue and Cry, nor with allurings and drawing back, nor with the common baits of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly practices, ſo that he was conſtrained to leave the purſute of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:118718:31"/>them, and to get before them, diſguiſing himſelf into ſome form or other that might beſt fit their diſpoſitions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he acteth with ſo much diligence and watchfulneſs thereunto, becauſe he hath a ſhort time to effect his deſigns, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.12. We unto the inhabiters of the earth and the ſea, for the Devil is come down unto you, having great wrath, becauſe he hath but a ſhort time, and it is ſhort indeed according to my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of time to the end of the Creation to make up ſeven thouſand years compleat,<note place="margin">The end of the world.</note> and no more, (I have in my apprehenſion a fair Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and reaſon for this) and of this there are not above thirteen hundred and fifty behinde, and out of this there muſt be a thouſand taken, wherein Satan ſhall be chained up and caſt into the bottomleſs Pit, <hi>Revel.</hi> 20. Reade all this Chapter, and ſee what you can underſtand therein.</p>
            <p>The thouſand years there ſpoken of I take literally according to our computation of time.</p>
            <p>The binding and chaining up of the Devil I take to be ſuch a powerfull and bleſſed appearance of God in the hearts of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who ſhall through the teachings of himſelf be brought to ſuch an holy Conformity and Uniformity, both in affection, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and walking, that <hi>Antichrist</hi> ſhall not be able to break in upon them; to delude or entice them, or the like; but they through the glorious and in dwelling of God in their hearts ſhall be able to reſiſt all the deceivable ways of Satan, that he will be as it were no Devil at all unto them, he will be as though he were tied with a Chain, or caſt into a Ple, not able to hurt or wrong any of them as now he doth.</p>
            <p>Now this thouſand years being taken out wherein the Church of CHRIST ſhall thus triumph over him, and conquer him, there remaineth but three hundred and fifty or there about, which muſt likewiſe be divided into two parts; one part muſt be for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan to go about into all the corners of the earth to deceive and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile the people again, <hi>v.</hi> 7, 8. at the exſpiration of the thouſand year, after the manner as now he doth in my judgment, and ſo to bring them into a ſtate of apoſtacy, which he cannot do probably under an age and a half, or two ages; for we ſee in our own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, there is no ground, error or ſuperſtition ſucked into the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118718:32"/>hearts of a people, or rooted out, under an age and an half at leaſt, and therefore I think he muſt have ſuch an allowance as this for to bring an univerſal apoſtacy into all the earth before its deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and if you ſhall allow him but an hundred and fifty years for this, then there wilbe but even two hundred before that thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, which is but a ſhort time in compariſon of what he hath had ever ſince he firſt beguiled <hi>Eve</hi> with the forbidden Apple; and therefore no marvel he doth ſo beſtir himſelf now, and finde out new and more dangerous ways.</p>
            <p>This is my preſent apprehenſion concerning the ending of the World, and concerning that myſtery in <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Si quid novisti rectius istis</l>
               <l>Candidus imperti, ſi non, his utere mecum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Question</hi> 2. In order to the people themſelves called <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Peradventure ſome are inquiring, ſeeing they are ſo exceedingly deluded and ſuch a dangerous people, what courſe ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by them, whether it were beſt to impriſon them, or baniſh them, or the like?</p>
            <p>In my Anſwer hereunto I ſhall direct my ſpeech unto two ſorts of people.</p>
            <p>Firſt, unto the common ſort of people. I do hear and believe it is true, that the ordinary ſort of people in all Countreys and Towns whither theſe poor creatures come, do abuſe them very much, and beat them, and deſpitefully uſe them; I do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that this is the right way to deal with them, neither can any good ground be given for this kinde of uſage of them, ſeeing they come to places in a peaceable manner, pretending they come for the peoples good, and me thinks it is great inhumanity to uſe any people ſo uncivilly that come ſo civilly, and withall they ſpeak nothing in that nature but what their hearers themſelves muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to be true, reproving them ſharply for ſome unjuſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous actings or other, or for ſome carnal and ſecure conditions wherein they live, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore I would counſel all ſuch people to whom they ſhall come in this kinde, to take a right way of oppoſing them; which is through a ſtrong knowledg and underſtanding of the Scripture to reaſon with them and to prove them fairly according
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:118718:32"/>to the rules of the Scripture, and ſuch rules as I have here given you in my Book, to be thoſe deluders and deluded people that are ſpoken of by <hi>Christ</hi> and his Apoſtles; and upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, neither to own them nor their Doctrine. This is the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable way of the Goſple, and I think I may be bold to tell you this for your encouragment, that if you ſhall ſtick up cloſely and unanimouſly to this way, you will finde the Devil a very Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, according to that word of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>James,</hi> Reſiſt the devil and he will fly from.</p>
            <p>But if any of you ſhall ſay, that you are not able to deal with them in this nature, they are too full of knowledg, and you are not ſo well acquainted with the Scriptures as they, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I fear it is too true as you ſay, but is not the fault your own? Hive not you Bibles as well as they? How comes it to paſs that you are ſo empty of knowledg in the Word of God, but for want of diligent reading and meditating in the ſame. And therefore I would counſel all men both Preachers and people, to be hereafter better armed againſt them, for I ſuppoſe you will be more troubled with them than you have been, and indeed when you have done all this, your natural attainments of this kinde will prove too ſhort to deal with them by; therefore by all means laber father, and feek to gain the ſpiritual armour of <hi>Christ Jeſus,</hi> which you ſhall have from him, if you will receive him, <hi>John</hi> 1.12. and hearken diligently unto the voice of God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you, and do not ſtand ſtill and reſt your ſelves ſatisfied in your ignorant and carnal conditions, but remember that word <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.14. Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ariſe from the dead, and <hi>Christ</hi> ſhall give thee light, yea and power, and ſtrength alſo to overcome the aſſaults of Satan; and you muſt pray with all your might unto the Lord to furniſh your ſouls with his grace and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, that you may be able to ſtand faſt in ſuch perillous times.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I direct my ſpeech unto the civil Magiſtrate, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him to conſider what he doth to theſe people, I hear they are from City to City, and Countrey to Countrey, perſecuted and impriſoned by you, but by what Law of yours I know not, I do not hear that they do tranſgreſs any of your Laws by ſinfull and unrighteous actings, (if they ſhould, I ſhall give my conſent they
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:118718:33"/>might have double puniſhment) if they do not, I would have you forbear them, and ſee that they have not greater grounds to ſpeak againſt your abominations than you have to puniſh them. I fear becauſe they tell you your own, many of you, they turn your Patience into Paſſion, and from thence rather than from any Principle you have to do juſtice you act againſt them; for if you were generally men poſſeſſed with a zeal to do juſtice we ſhould not have ſuch abominable and crying ſins, calling at the Throne of God for juſtice againſt ſuch injuſticers as many are.</p>
            <p>If you will not believe the Truth becauſe it comes from them, yet I hope you will believe it as it comes from the mouth of God, <hi>Iſai</hi> 1.23, 24. Thy Princes are rebellious and companions of Thieves, every one loveth gifts, and followeth after rewards, they judg not the fatherleſs, neither doth the cauſe of the widow come before them; therefore ſaith the Lord, I will eaſe me of mine adverſaties and avenge me of mine enemies. And I would deſire you to reade judiciouſly over moſt part of the ſecond Chapter of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> there you ſhall finde the minde of God againſt ſelf-ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and pride, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that my counſel may appear more fully, I ſhall deſire you to give me leave to inſtruct you with much love and ſingle-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs in theſe two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that you will carefully in the fear of the Lord ſee to your ſelves and your ways, that theſe people may not charge you juſtly with any coverouſneſs, pride, vain-glory, ſelf-ſeeking, oppreſſion, or injuſtice, or profane and looſe walking, and in ſo doing you will in a moſt victorious manner diſarm them of their offenſive weapons.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that you would with all poſſible diligence ſeek for the armour of <hi>Christ Jeſus,</hi> and have your ſelves ſtrengthned with that faith and knowledg which comes from him, and theſe will be your defenſive weapons, and then by that time you ſhall have diſarmed them and armed your ſelves in this kinde, I know you will prove ſo able to deal with them your ſelves that you will never need to cry for your Sergeants and Officers to impriſon them.</p>
            <p>This I apprehend to be the moſt Goſpel-like and moſt honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able way for Magiſtrates, Miniſters and People to take againſt the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:118718:33"/>
            <p> I have now through the good hand of the Lord attained unto the end of my thoughts and mediatations about this myſterious work and workers, and have no more behinde but a few ſingle words, and then I have done.</p>
            <p>Let not any wonder while I am ſpeaking ſome particular words in a particular manner, that I have not a word for the <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſeeing they have been the whole object of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe: my reaſon is, becauſe I finde the ſtrongeſt of them to be beyond all hopes of returning or being convinced by ſuch means, for I have had ſome trial by reaſonings with them, and writings unto them, and I finde it bringeth forth nothing in them but more obdurateneſs of heart, and ſome railing, unchriſtian-like expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in their Letters; ſo that I chuſe rather to leave them to the wiſdom and power of God in this thing, and ſhall onely give theſe Cautions to ſuch younglings of them who never were yet in any powerfull working of the Truth and Light of <hi>Christ,</hi> and are but as it were entring into that deceitfull condition.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. With ſpeed forſake their ſociety wholly, both in publick and private manner; for although they may not prevail upon a knowing Chriſtian, yet they may eaſily carry away your hearts.</item>
               <item>2. Adjoyn your ſelves unto the ſocieties of ſuch people eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially who walk according to the moſt plain and ſure Rules of the Goſpel, and they are the Baptiſts, ſo called.</item>
               <item>3. If there be any power or faculty to pray left in you, I would have you uſe it to the utmoſt, deſiring the Lord in ſincerity and with diligence from time to time to teach and ſhew you the ways that you ſhall chuſe, and then to eſtabliſh and keep you in the ſame; and undoubtedly if the Lord through his mercy will be pleaſed to help you to obſerve theſe three things, it may be much for his glory and your comfort.</item>
            </list>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Firſt, a word to the <hi>Seekers</hi> ſo called.</head>
               <p>You are that progeny of mankinde or parentage of people, that have born forth unto the world that uncomfortable frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Ranters.</hi> Theſe brethren in iniquity are now in a ſtate of deſperate apoſtacy, who were once a people of moſt bleſſed principles and great attainments, for which things ſake I was in my affections and judgment engaged to maintain fellowſhip and ſociety with them in a ſpecial manner above and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:118718:34"/>beyond all other people profeſſing the ways of the Lord, for the ſpace of ſix years compleat.</p>
               <p>For the worth of thoſe principles ſake which did ſo much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect me, I ſhall make bold to mention three above the reſt in this place.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Was their readineſs and willingneſs to own and receive any farther manifeſtations or appearances of God in power and truth that he ſhould be pleaſed to ſhew unto them; and this was no ſmall mercy or attainment, when I conſider how many other poor creatures are poſſeſſed with a ſelfiſh, rigid principle, crying out againſt any farther manifeſtations or operations of God than what they have received, as Hereſie, Error, and the like.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Was their chearfull owning and embracing all the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the grace of God in truth that did appear in the hearts of any poor creatures, with much love and tender-heartedneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them.</p>
               <p>This was much, compared with the frame of ſpirit that poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth moſt profeſſors.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Was a greater careand ſeeking after a power, life, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit from the Lord, to perform their worſhip and duty withall, then ſtanding upon the form or outward appearance of ſuch wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or duty.</p>
               <p>Which 3. Principles as I did, ſo I do own them and judg them to be very heavenly and ſpiritual, onely by theſe poor creatures ſad example, I hope I ſhall be more carefull to try well what I receive under either of them. As you ſee theſe to be very high and ſpiritual, ſo they ly very open to temptation and deceit. And I will ſhew all people how Satan hath inſinuated himſelf into the hearts of theſe people under every one of theſe principles, and that with a very fair and unknowne guile.</p>
               <p>Firſt, whereas they were ever ready and willing to receive all further diſcoveries and manifeſtations from the Lord, he tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming himſelf into an Angel of Light, that ſo he might ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly act the part of God, hath preſented ſome new things or ways and operations un o them, more ſeemingly ſpiritual than any they had before, ſuch as you have ſeen throughout this book, and ſo eaſily engageth their hearts to receive what their principles led them unto.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:118718:34"/>
               <p> Secondly, they being very tenderly affected to all ſuch whom they judged to be ſincere, although under the loweſt diſcovery of truth. Here Satan deceiving of them maketh them to become very much affected with the carnal creatures of the world, and to diſown ſuch as they formerly owned and tendered, under ſmall attainments, as though they were in a worſe eſtate than meer carnal and atheiſtical perſons.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in as much as they did more look after the power of godlineſs than the form, and more after ſpiritual enablings of the ſoule to duties than its going forth in its own ſtrength. Here the Deceiver beguileth them, and carrieth them firſt away from that form they did uſe; and ſecondly, under waiting for ſpiritual endowments he ſuggeſteth by fits much power of ſpeaking and praying likewiſe, for he can enable men to pray as well as to ſpeak rumable words. I know this to be true, for when ſome of them have been under the greateſt deluſion that might be in ſpeaking, they have been carried out to pray in as ample man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and as good language as ever I prayed when I enjoyed moſt of the divine operations and preſence of God. I can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs this ſeveral times.</p>
               <p>And becauſe you ſhall have a little farther diſcovery of this, I will turn you over unto a book of <hi>Hannah Trapnels,</hi> if ever you have ſeen it, ſhe was a maid in <hi>London,</hi> that as I have heard by credible reporte, would be caſt into traunces and ſwounings, ſometimes a whole day and a whole night, and ſometimes twelve hours, that to the view of the beholders ſhe would be dead, and yet in the coming out of thoſe fits would ſometimes ſpeak, and ſometimes pray, as though ſhe had been an Angel from Heaven, I have ſeen her Book, and that which I was ſtumbled at, (even in thoſe times when I thought ſhe was ſent as an Angel from God to ſpeak unto men, rather than one deluded by <hi>Antichrist</hi>) was that confuſion that was in her ſpirit about <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> as ſhe calls him: for ſometimes, for one while ſhe would be raging, and raving, and railing at him with ſuch kinde of language that I never heard any ſervant of CHRIST uſe, and another while it may be in the ſame breath praying for him again with ſuch words and expreſſions that were admirable; and ſome of the beholders ſtanding by that could write ſhort-hand took moſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:118718:35"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:118718:35"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:118718:36"/>of her expreſſions, for ſhe was but ſlow in delivery.</p>
               <p>That Book will give any one a perfect form of <hi>Antichrists</hi> teaching men to pray and to ſpeak, and withall to propheſie a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; for in many things in that Book ſhe is like a Prophet; and although it be in undeniable words and expreſſions peradventure, yet I am ſure the Spirit of God doth not act any of his people to pray and curſe ſo both in a breath; and as for <hi>Oliver</hi> that ſhe ſpeaketh ſo much of, the ſe vants of CHRIST are not acted to rage nor rail againſt him, but to ſpeak with wiſdom and ſound judgment when they tell him of what they conceive amiſs in him.</p>
               <p>This buſineſs of praying, whereat many ſimple people might ſtumble as much, if not more, than any thing elſe they ſee by them yet, hath procured theſe Lines; and I hope this may be a uſefull hint to one and many.</p>
               <p>Here you have ſeen the <hi>Seekers</hi> Principles, which the <hi>Quakers</hi> hold yet entirely, becauſe they are acted as Miniſters of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, But as for the <hi>Ranters,</hi> they have had new Principles or apprehenſions added unto theſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That God is all in all things, and that all things are God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. That God is all in all in them, and they all in him, and then by conſequence they are not themſelves, neither can do any thing of themſelves, but God acteth and doth all in them and by them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. That God acting all in them will act nothing againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and all that he doth muſt be good, and therefore whatſoever they do muſt be good, becauſe they are acted thereunto of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to the pure all things are pure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Ranters</hi> are the moſt unworthy of all ſorts of creatures that ever were known, and I reckon them far more wicked than any other profane, wicked people; in as much as profane men (be they never ſo wicked) dare not juſtifie their ungodly deeds; but theſe deluded creatures juſtifie their actings, and reckon them perfect, pure and good, as being done of God. There were a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple deluded and acted after the very ſame manner as theſe are in the days of the Apoſtles, for ſuch were they of whom <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeak of, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Jude</hi> the beginning to <hi>v.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>Moſt of all thoſe Apoſtates in the days of the Apoſtles were
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:118718:36"/>acted like unto theſe <hi>Ranters</hi> now, or elſe as meer worldlings, like unto <hi>Demas</hi> forſaking all former profeſſions of the faith and Goſpel to embrace this preſent world. I can hardly finde any in reading all the New Teſtament that were acted as Miniſters of Righteouſneſs as theſe <hi>Quakers</hi> are; and I ſuppoſe they were onely foreſeen and propheſied of againſt this time, by <hi>Christ</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> here in my Tex, and in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 41, 2, 3.</p>
               <p>Herein I obſerve not only the ſubtilty but alſo the diligence of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> who finding his time to be ſhort, and willing to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large his Kingdom, acteth his ſervants ſeveral ways under ſeveral pretences and forms, that ſo ſuch as would not be held in through open profaneneſs, becauſe they themſelves do condemn and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own it in their judgments, might be brought to ſee (through a Lie in Hypocriſie) that there is no ſin at all but to him that doth ſo eſteem it, and upon that account to juſtifie all their ways and actions, laying it all upon the ſcore of God, ſaying he doth all in them and by them, they are wholly crucified into the will of the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And again, ſuch as would not be deceived by him in neither of both theſe ways, might be acted as Miniſters of Righteouſneſs, as falſe Apoſtles or falſe <hi>Christs,</hi> not being ſeen either to own or to practice any uncleanneſs at all, but rather to be ready to do all good, as <hi>Christ</hi> and the Apoſtles were. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that I have ſometimes told theſe <hi>Quakers,</hi> that I did conceive the deſign of <hi>Antichrist</hi> was in the end to bring them to work all manner of uncleanneſs, but ſince I have taken far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notice of the propheſies of Scripture concerning them, and alſo noting that Satan hath acted another ſort of people that way already, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Ranters,</hi> I do now judg that they ſhall be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on from one degree unto another to act righteouſneſs all along, as I have declared at large before.</p>
               <p>In what I have lately writ, all the world may ſee that <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ</hi> doth act three manner of ways in three ſorts of people.</p>
               <p>But little did I think once to have ſeen the people called the <hi>Seekers,</hi> whom I did eſteem to be ſo heavenly and ſpiritual both in principle and practice, carried away with ſuch ſpiritual deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and truly I fear there are but few of them but what are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared already, ſo that I know not whether any admonition here may come ſoon enough for their prevention, yet rather than I
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:118718:37"/>would ſpare my Pen for a few Lines, if it might be, but for the ſake of very few in this Nation, I will tell them what I apprehend they ought to do with ſpeed.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Either to conſort themſelves among themſelves, and regain their loſt time, and exerciſe their fading graces.</item>
                  <item>2. To joyn themſelves into the ſocieties of other ſervants of <hi>Christ,</hi> and eſpecially ſuch as do live the beſt life, and walk moſt agreeable to the order of the Goſpel.</item>
               </list>
               <p>For I know no other ordinary way of preventing the deluſion from ſuch as are yet eſcaped. But me thinks I have ſtrong perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that all of them will be hurried up and down unto one of theſe ſhamefull conditions of <hi>Ranters, Quakers,</hi> or meer world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. I have too much reaſon for what I ſpeak.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond word to the people called <hi>Baptists.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I have been a great while ſince convinced that you are the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who are beſt able, according to the exemplary rules of <hi>Christ</hi> and his Apoſtles in the Goſpel, to prove your ſelves to be the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church of <hi>Christ</hi> amongſt men, being neceſſitated by my Antagoniſts in a publick diſputation againſt Infant-baptiſm to fly unto your practice and rules for my own defence, ever ſince which time I have more and more ſeen the clearneſs therof, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not yet carried forth to the practice thereof my ſelf, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Lord did not require any of our ages to walk ſo, but yet did very gladly own and receive ſuch who out of ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of conſcience and obedience to <hi>Christ</hi> did take it up, thinking alſo that it was but a creaturely act whereunto any car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal man might be brought through the convictions of his own heart, as well as <hi>Simon Magus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But indeed that which I conceive did moſt keep me from it, was theſe comforts and refreſhments which I do receive from the Lord without it, and having alſo communion with my former ſociety, which now is wholly broke off through the myſterious workings of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and I am afraid that I ſhall receive ſome Eclipſe of my former enjoyments and divine operations, yet I know whom I have believed, which thing if it ſhall be joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the loſs of my communion with Creatures, I hope they ſhall produce much diligence to inquire further into that admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Baptiſm, and make me more entirely one in the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:118718:37"/>will of the Lord concerning it, and I would gladly deſire you upon the terms of Chriſtian love to uſe often thoſe words of <hi>Paul, Col.</hi> 1.9, 10, 11. and when you uſe them, let me be your object, as the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> were <hi>Pauls;</hi> and I would deſire you alſo to walk ſo dexterouſly, that you might ever more and more prove your ſelves to be the Church and Diſciples of <hi>Christ,</hi> and that you would endeavour to remove all things that might be an occaſion of ſtumbling to any weak creatures, and that you would ſo far deny your ſelves that you might not live in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of ſuch things which neither <hi>Christ</hi> not his Apoſtles would by any means allow of.</p>
               <p>The Lord help you and me to walk blameleſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A third word to my Book.</head>
               <p>While I have ſaluted ſo many by the way, I cannot chuſe but bid thee Farewell alſo, telling thee, that as thou art like to be a great Traveller, ſo thou muſt expect to paſs through evil report and good report, through honor and diſhonor, as a deceiver and yet true, thou muſt become ſubject to every mans judgment, the godly and the wicked, the learned and the ignorant, the wife man and the fool; but regard it not, it is that common deſtiny of others with thee; and thou maiſt expect to hear very ſuddenly a mighty Hue and Cry ſent after thee (as though thou waſt ſome notorious Thief or Robber) by him who will act like a roaring Lion in thoſe that are his ſervants at command, endeavouring thereby to hinder thy travels, knowing that thou maiſt be a great means of deſtroying his Kingdom; he will queſtionleſs, as he dealt by the Woman <hi>Revel.</hi> 12. ſo by thee, caſt a mighty floud out of his mouth of all manner of opprobries, Lies, and diſgracefull railing ſpeeches; but if there be no other means the Earth ſhall help the Woman, thou needeſt not be afraid of being overcome, becauſe as the truth of him who is ſaid to be Truth it ſelf, in whom there is ſaid to be more power and ſtrength for the propagation than in all thine Enemies, be they men or devils, for thy oppoſition; therefore expect not from me (who am but in that reſpect thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant) any defence by raiſing an Army of Reaſonings, Argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and Diſputings either by my Pen or words.</p>
               <p>But go forth like a Man of War in thy own power and ſtrength, and in the Name of the Lord be proſperous.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
